<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Le chemin abregé. Or, A compendious method for the attaining of sciences in a short time Together with the statutes of the Academy founded by the Cardinall of Richelieu. Englished by R.G. Gent.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79446</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3779A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223591</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895416</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895416</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152885</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79446)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152885)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2330:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Le chemin abregé. Or, A compendious method for the attaining of sciences in a short time Together with the statutes of the Academy founded by the Cardinall of Richelieu. Englished by R.G. Gent.</title>
                  <author>Gentili, Robert, 1590-1654?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Humphrey Moseley, at the Princes Armes in St Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Robert Gentilis.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Richelieu, Armand Jean du Plessis, --  duc de, 1585-1642 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Science --  Methodology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Science --  Philosophy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Richelieu (France) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152885:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Le Chemin Abregé.</hi> Or, A Compendious METHOD for the Attaining of Sciences in a Short Time.</p>
            <p>Together with the Statutes of the ACADEMY Founded by the Cardinall of <hi>RICHELIEU.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Engliſhed by</hi> R. G. <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> at the <hi>Princes Armes</hi> in St <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="to Selden" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152885:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152885:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull <hi>JOHN SELDEN,</hi> Eſquier.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Have often deſired an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to teſtifie both to your ſelf, and the World, how much I honour your tranſcendent Learning. This Peece comming to my hands to tranſlate, I pit ch'd upon your ſelf to beg your patronage for it. Some perhaps may urge, it deſerves not your Acceptance: the greater then will your Candour appear in deſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:152885:3"/>at from the overhasty cenſure of raſh Criticks. It was a Speech made to the famous Cardinall <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelieu,</hi> who is acknowledged by all to have been the grand Politick States man, either of his own, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent times. But neither this, nor the Cardinals good Approbation of it, are the onely cauſes of my Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>This, Sir, is an excellent Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a beautifull Structure. It Containes an exact Method for the trayning up of youth in all manner of Sciences, and in ſo ſhort a time as no former Age afforded the like: and I am confident this our Preſent cannot chooſe but approve of. But to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all Scrupulous doubts, from the common Reader, whether our Author hath ſet down the right way to atcheive this ſo laudable an Enterpriſe, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to your Judicious Approbation. If You think my labour well beſtowed, I ſhall think my felf happy: if not, I
<pb facs="tcp:152885:3"/>muſt fry to your Courteous Clement aſſuring my ſelfe of your pardon for my bold Intruſion, which I hope you will look upon as only my Ambition to deerve the Title of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble Servant,</hi> Robert Gentilis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="to others" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152885:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152885:4"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST NOBLE, and moſt Excellent Mr. <hi>PETER EISSINGH,</hi> Magiſtrate of the Cittie of <hi>Groninghe,</hi> and Overſeer of the Academie: <hi>Mr Oſebrandt John Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> Commiſſarie for the managing of the affaires of <hi>Omland,</hi> and overſeer of the Academie. Mr <hi>Jodocus Heinſius Syndicus,</hi> and Councellor of <hi>Omland,</hi> and Overſeer of the Academie.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His diſcourſe which will ſeem Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxicall both to the learned and unlearned, doth not promiſe it ſelf to be ſo perſwaſive to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as to draw them all to ſide with the Author in his opinion. Himſelf had no ſuch pretence; which cauſed him, after he had once put it to the preſs, to call it in again. I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:152885:5"/>ſuppreſſed it, had not ſome perſons of worth deſired to ſee it, which hath cauſed mee to publiſh it. Yet the Reader may find herein, what were the thoughts and intentions; of one of the greateſt Politicians of our age. Thoſe who wonder, why <hi>Socrates, Platoe's,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Schooles, yeeld no more <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minonda's, Xenophons,</hi> nor <hi>Alexanders,</hi> ſhall here find ſatisfaction. Theſe great men made Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as it were, naturall to them, and cauſed them to grow up with them, giving them the Principles thereof in their infancy, Whereas now, the flower of mans youth is imployed in learning of the Precepts of obſolet Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages; and after he hath gotten this vocall knowledge, when he comes to any reall, he meets with ſome unskillfull and ſhufling teachers, who either through ignorance, or out of meer malice, obſcure Arts and Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, under rude and improper termes, cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing them, as I may ſay, with raggs and tat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Blame me not then, gentlemen, if I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you this treatiſe: there being none, or but very few extant upon ſuch a Subject. Your affections to learning, and knowledge of it hath perſwaded me, that ſuch births as theſe ought to have approbation, or diſacceptance from ſuch as you are. I know there are many things in it, at which weak underſtandings may ſtumble. They will ſay, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſeeks with unexampled boldneſs, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue ancient Languages, to gain more tye and auctority to his own native tongue. But thoſe who ſhall conſider, that all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:152885:5"/>may apply that which is here particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken of the <hi>French,</hi> aſwell to their own mother tongue, will ſoone acquit him of that imputation. You muſt moreover obſerve that he doth not abſolutely diſſwade any from the ſtudy of thoſe he calls Obſolet Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but onely reſtraines it within the bounds of a publick utility: He approves of learning of thoſe Languages, ſo we do it as the <hi>Greeks</hi> did the <hi>Aegiptiack,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Arabians</hi> the <hi>Greek,</hi> namely to appropriate to their own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſuch Sciences as were firſt conceived and written in the other. It were abſurd to ſay, that we cannot in our Languages doe the like; For reaſon ſpeaks all Languages, and through the neceſſity of expreſſing ones ſelf, all Nations (were they never ſo barbarous) did, &amp; do dayly find out termes &amp; words ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to expreſs their thoughts. Is mans un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding become ſo confined, and barren, that it cannot more dreſs and trimm up Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences after its own faſhion? No indeed, it is as vigorous now as it was in former ages, but more ſervile. It is become like thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generous and ſlowthfull painters, who dare not adventure to ſee forth any thing of their own invention; But will rather bee ſtiled poor coppiers of others draughts, then by ſome Maſterpecce of their owne, ſhew that they underſtand the ſecret and order of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning. And are content to beſtow the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of their art, and ſpend their times in refreſhing ſome old images, and renewing with ſome quaint colours, the pourtraiture
<pb facs="tcp:152885:6"/>of a <hi>Judith</hi> and <hi>Holofernes.</hi> It is no wonder therefore, if our modern Languages be ſo poor, ſeeing we beſtow all the care we ſhould have of them, upon the beautifying and refining of the antient ones, whoſe very Antiquity o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe is a manifeſt proof of their defect and barrenneſſe. For as thoſe who ſpake them, had ſeen fewer things then we, ſo they needed fewer words to expreſs them: and living in the firſt ages of the world, they could not frame names for ſuch things as have been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered but of late dayes. So that we may there find the miſtake of thoſe Criticks, who through a curious ſtupidity, will forſake Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolets of weight for light Medalls. As for thoſe who imagine, that treating of Sciences in vulgar tongues, will derogate from their Majeſty, I beleive they have as little ground for it, as thoſe who ſhould conceive that the value of Gold is diminiſhed by thoſe who digg it out of the entralls of the earth, to refine it, and make it ſerve for commerce. Finally Gentlemen, thoſe who ſhall know how to diſtinguiſh the Authors reaſons, from the praiſes which he attributes to the perſon to whom he ſpeaks; that is to ſay, can diſcern the matter from the accidents, the ſubſtance from the colours, and the words of truth from thoſe of inſinuation, ſhal find that it would be very advantagious for every country, to have ſuch Sciences, as concerne Policy, taught in their mother tongue. And let ſuch as are of a contrary opinion, look upon this Treatiſe, as a triall of wit, and read it onely to paſs the
<pb facs="tcp:152885:6"/>time. My onely deſire is, to ſhew you that my duty and affection cauſed me to dedicate it to you all joyntly; deſiring not to be known by any other name, then of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble and obedient Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152885:7"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>COurteous Reader, This ſpeech was made in the preſence of one of the ableſt Politicians of our age. Wherefore wonder not at the ſublime titles which our author gives him. I might have left them out, but I held it not fit to alter any thing, either in the matter or forme of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. There is a ſecond ſpeech, which I ſhall alſo preſent you with, if I perceive you accept of this. I have in the mean time imitated the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Prieſts, who were wont to burn a little of the hair of the beaſt, which they intended to offer, to make an eſsay by the ſmoak therof, whether the offering would be accepted or no. Reade, and judge favourably. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text_of_speech">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152885:7"/>
            <head>The Firſt Speech made in the preſence of <hi>The Late Cardinall of</hi> RICHELIEV.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the French Academie was firſt eſtabliſhed by your Eminency for the reforming and refining of our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, thoſe who are verſed in Hiſtorie, did preſage the imminent glory of this Monarchie: having often read and obſerved, that Monarchies, and Common-wealths never flouriſhed more then when the Native Language firſt was riſen to its full perfection; as the corruption thereof was alwaies a certain forerunner of the ruine of Nations, and decay of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires.</p>
            <p>The regulating of words doth inſenſiblie produce in all places a conformity of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which is the ſtrongeſt bond that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152885:8"/>may be, to conjoyne the various affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of people under one government, and keepe them in a perfect correſpondencie, wherein conſiſts the happineſſe and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of all States<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> uniting them in a true underſtanding of each other, wherein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the happineſſe and proſperity of States. Wherfore they who firſt founded Cities for humane ſocietie, and all the wiſe Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians who ſucceeded them, tooke as much care for the beautifying and refining their Language, as for any other either Sacred or Civill buſineſſe, namely Fundamentall Lawes, Myſteries of Religion, or the moſt holy Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>The greateſt Divines affirme, that the firſt Language after the Creation was eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way accompliſht &amp; compleat, as well in its entire ſtructure, as invention, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. Becauſe our firſt father who had an infuſed knowledge of all things, gave them their names according to their ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall vertue and propertie. By this meanes did he communicate his knowledge to his poſterity, making it eaſie for them to grow up to underſtanding, onely by learning to ſpeake; being without any other precepts inſtructed in all manner of knowledge. This language was of ſuch efficacie, that every word was as a whole Science, which truly declared the Eſſence and Nature of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152885:8"/>every thing: whereby man, who naturally deſires to know, found his deſires fulfilled, and ſatisfied without any difficulty. Hee began to Philoſophate, and learne how to live well, even from his birth and infancy. The intention of this firſt man, who was framed by the immediate hand of God, was to make this language invaria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and univerſall, and (for the benefit of his poſterity) the character &amp; lively ſpring of all thoſe rare lights, which God of his goodneſſe had infuſed in him. All ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing languages have been moſt confuſed, barren, and imperfect; by reaſon that men being become incapable of communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea &amp; even of ſociety, through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of languages, did almoſt loſe the uſe of diſcourſe, and lived for a time like ſavages and vagabonds. It was a horrible diſorder amongſt mankind, and a terrible curſe upon the builders of Babel.</p>
            <p>But as ſoone as men began a little to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociate, &amp; reunite themſelves, every one in his own family invented names for ſuch common things as were moſt neceſlarie for mans ordinary uſe, and then (as it is now adayes in new diſcovered countries) there were as many Idioms as Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties. Atlength (through ſucceſſion of tims) men beginning to rallie and gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and lay the foundations of a civill
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152885:9"/>life, all theſe particular Languages ceaſed, and they agreed upon one common Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage for the mutuall underſtanding of people.</p>
            <p>True it is, that there remaines no monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments amongſt us in theſe times of thoſe Languages which were in thoſe primitive Empires of the world, <hi>Aſſyrians, Egyptians,</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> unleſſe it be upon ſome Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mides and Medalls, of which the worth and ſignification is not known in our dayes. But the Chaldean and Egyptian Prieſts and Magitians, who taught all manner of Sciences in their mother tongue, witneſs ſufficiently, that they had carefully refined it: ſeeing that the firſt (after the confuſion of Languages) invented ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient tearmes, not onely for ordinary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and commerce, but alſo for the ſublimeſt ſpeculative Sciences, Myſteries of Religion, and in a word for all manner of ſecret things, which came not to the knowledge of vulgar people.</p>
            <p>The and ent Gaules, though they were ſo much addicted to warre, that becauſe they would not bee troubled with any other thing, they left the judging of Law ſuits, the governing of Politicke buſineſs and all other peaceable affaires to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by their wives; And had a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall law amongſt themſelves to ſet
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152885:9"/>forth every ſeventy yeares, two hundred thouſand choyce fighting men in the field, and ſend them away out of their owne Kingdome to conquer ſome other country. Yet ſo carefull were they of maintayning and refining their native language, that the <hi>Bards</hi> and <hi>Semnotheans,</hi> who were their Poets, have been thought to exceede the Greek and Latine ones: And it is no ſmall honour to this country, that we read even in Roman Hiſtories, how that <hi>Statius Cecilius, a Gaule,</hi> was Schoolemaſter to <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> the ancienteſt of their Poets, and that the ſaid <hi>Cecilius</hi> together with <hi>Valerius Cato,</hi> another <hi>Gaule,</hi> were the firſt that brought Poetrie to Rome. And in thoſe dayes the ordinary employme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Noble mens chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were to make verſes, and learne all manner of ſciences in their own mother tongue. And the Greekes doe not onely confeſſe they had their characters and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of their Alphabet from the <hi>Gaules;</hi> but even <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelfe (as <hi>Laertius</hi> reports) freely confeſſes that they borrowed their Philoſophie of our <hi>Druids</hi> and <hi>Semnotheans;</hi> whereby we may know, that our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were as skilfull in Sciences, as they were practiſed in well ſpeaking: and that they are not without reaſon eſteemed to have been the Authors of Phyſicall and Morall Philoſophie, Geometrie, and other
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152885:10"/>learning, which had its originall amongſt them, and was from thence ſpread abroad into other countries. For although Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie be naturall to all men, and hath ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively flouriſhed in many parts of the world; yet one may in ſome manner ſay, that ours is its native countrie, and that it is more proper and naturall to this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then to any other; ſeeing that when it was utterly extinguiſhed in <hi>Egypt, Greece,</hi> and <hi>Arabia,</hi> yet it remaieed ſtill in this country, in deſpight of all the revolutions and changes of State, which uſually alter and turne every thing upſide downe.</p>
            <p>As ſoone as the <hi>Grecians</hi> had attained to any domination, they uſed their beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours both to refine and perfect their Language, and alſo to make it extend to the neighbouring provinces: its originall atfirſt was in that little countrie, which was called <hi>Hellas;</hi> and afterwards it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over into the Kingdomes of <hi>Epirus</hi> and <hi>Macedonia</hi> the Iſlands of the <hi>Aegean</hi> Sea, <hi>Candie, Corfu, Egypt, Rhodes, Natolia, Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Euxinus, Trebizond,</hi> to the very mouth of <hi>Danubius, Thrace, Sicily,</hi> and all the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne coaſt of <hi>Italie,</hi> to the very confines of <hi>France,</hi> which extend from the <hi>Rhoſne</hi> to <hi>Genoa;</hi> it being certaine that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeilles</hi> was once a Colonie of the <hi>Phoceans.</hi> Their Annalls teſtifie that the <hi>Areopagus</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152885:10"/>had the charge of refining the Language; &amp; the <hi>Areopagites</hi> did oftentimes meet for the ſetting of the genuine meaning &amp; true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of a letter, or anaccent: &amp; to it muſt be attributed the glorie of preſerving this language the ſtructure of which is ſo admirable in all its parts, that it hath ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for a Modell &amp; Idea to the Latine, &amp; other Languages that have beene ſince. And when the Greekes were divided into ſeverall States, that diviſion occaſioned as many ſeverall Dialects, as there were Common-wealths, whereof each one ſtrove who ſhould moſt poliſh &amp; beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy its own manner of ſpeaking: As if they would have noted the difference of their Soveraigneties by ſome diverſity of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: So that now reading thoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours whoſe works are yet extant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, we can hardly judge which of them hath moſt refined his Dialect.</p>
            <p>The Roman Senate (the wiſeſt, and moſt venerable aſſemblie of the world) judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be no leſſe advantageous for their Republick to amplifie their Language, then to extend their frontiers, had reſolved to make it as univerſall as their domination. For the effecting of which glorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, they ſent out Colonies into all parts, and gave the greateſt cities of thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries which they had conquered the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152885:11"/>of Roman freedom to oblige them to ſpeake their language, without which they might not be capeable of bearing any Office in the common-wealth. They alſo made decrees, that no forraigne buſineſſe, ſuites, and Embaſſies ſhould be diſcuſſed in the Senate, but in Latine, their Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall lawes ſhould bee written in it, and their Prators and Governors of conquered Provinces ſhould give judgement in no other Language. It was a policie religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly obſerved by the Roman Magiſtrates, never to give any Audience to any ſtrange Language, denying that privildge even to the Greeke, though it were famous and celebrated amongſt them. They alſo ſet up publike Grammer Schooles, to inſtruct and bring up youth in the Latine tongue in all cities of their Dominions. Theſe were the meanes by which theſe great Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lititians ſpread their language throughout the world, and taught <hi>Africk, Spaine, France, Italie, Germanie, Valachia, England,</hi> and divers other Northern Regions to ſpeake Latine, untill the diſſipation of that Empire. They had not (I muſt confeſſe) the like ſucceſſe towards the Eaſt, becauſe the Greek, which by reaſon of Sciences, was there in its luſter, did that way ſtay the courſe of the Latine tongue.</p>
            <p>No ſooner did the <hi>Arabians</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152885:11"/>to build their greatneſſe upon the ruines of the Roman Empire, but they preſently began likewiſe to refine, extend, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie their I anguage, and having ſubd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d a great part of <hi>Aſia, Africa</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> they brought it into divers Eaſtern, Southerne, and weſterne countries, and made it ſpread as far, or farther then any other, that we have yet knowne</p>
            <p>The Turkes, though they be enemies of Sciences, having baniſht them out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, Greece,</hi> and <hi>Arabia,</hi> doe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding intrude their Language into all the countries which they conquer, cauſing the people to make uſe of it in their milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie offaire;, and all publike acts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments. And though the Arabick tongue be the beautifulleſt, and richeſt of any Nationall Language now extant, and be yet uſed in Egypt for an Interpreter of their Religion, and Alcoran: yet doe they inſlave the Inhabitants to the rigor of this law, to deſtroy it utterly by degrees, and bring in the Turkiſh Speech in ſtead of it.</p>
            <p>The Spaniards likewiſe, whoſe domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are hard to be preſerved, the parts ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being ſo farre diſtant one from the other, had no ſooner laid the foundations of their Vniverſal monarchie, but they indeavored
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152885:12"/>to the uttermoſt of their power, to ſpread their Language, not onely in thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries which they had gotten in <hi>Africk</hi> &amp; <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> but have extended it even into <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica.</hi> So that <hi>Peru,</hi> which is alſo called the <hi>Golden Caſtile,</hi> though above fifteene hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred leagues diſtant from <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſpeakes now no longer its own, but hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained as well as the reſt to imbrace the conquerers language. <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Spaine</hi> forced the <hi>Moores</hi> of <hi>Granada</hi> to change their habit and ſpeech, for no other reaſon, but onely to keepe ſo many different and ſeverall Nations in perfect union and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, by a conformity in all things.</p>
            <p>Finally the <hi>French</hi> tongue onely hath had the ill fortune to remaine for a long ſeaſon deformed, rough, and irregular, though the Nation hath alwaies been po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and glorious; not through any bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe or defect in the French Genius, for both the Greekes and Romans have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies given pregnant teſtimonies of their eloquence; but the beginning of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order began in <hi>Iulius Caeſars</hi> time, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conquered the <hi>Gaules</hi> (the better to ſubject them to the Romiſh yoake) extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated the ancient <hi>Gaules</hi> baniſhed our <hi>Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ides,</hi> who were the onely depoſitories of our Lawes, Religion, and Sciences, that he might finde ſo much the leſſe reſiſtance
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152885:12"/>to the introduction of Roman Cuſtomes. Afterwards the Northerne nations, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Franconians, Gothes, Hunns, Vandalls,</hi> and others, going in queſt of a milder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>mate, and more fruitfull countries, made ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inrodes into this, came and inhabited part of it, whence proceeded the mixture, and confuſion which we may this day ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in it. For on that ſide of <hi>France</hi> which is next to <hi>Germany</hi> and the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> it received many harſh words, of a difficult and hard pronunciation; towards <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> it retained many Latine words. And afterwards being divided into ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtates, each people contained them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves within the bounds of their owne precincts, which hindred the free com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce one with another: and this ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion framed as many ſeverall Dialects <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, as there were Principa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>The hatred which the Romans bare the Gaules, by reaſon of their valout, and the frequent victories they had gotten of them, was ſo exceſſive and inveterate, that ranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acking and pillaging the whole countrie, they ſuppreſſed all the bookes, writings, and records of the <hi>Semnotheans, Bards,</hi> and <hi>Druides.</hi> And the Emperour <hi>Tiberi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to extingiſh the name of <hi>Gaules,</hi> interdicted the Prieſts to ſacrifice, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152885:13"/>a falſe pretence of Magick, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, wherewith he accuſed them, he drove them all out of the country. <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus</hi> the Emperour was no leſſe an enemy to them, though hee tooke a farr milder and more politick way to ruine them. For conſidering that the beſt way to make our forefathers forget what things had been done before, was to annihilate and aboliſh their native Language, hee did not onely command them to learne the Latine, and to pleade therein, &amp; to make thoſe Hymnes which they ſung in their ſacrifices, in that language; but forbad them likewiſe to treate of any matters with the Emperors by meanes of any interpreter; ſaying it was a thing misbeſeeming Roman greatneſſe, to be ſpoken to by a ſubjects Language. Yet neither theſe, nor the ſucceeding Emperours could utterly aboliſh the Gaules Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: And notwithſtanding all theſe violent courſes, ſome Colledges which the Bards had erected in divers cities, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at <hi>Treves, Autun, Beſanson, Tolous, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeilles,</hi> and <hi>Lyons,</hi> ſtood many yeares after. But as ſoone as they had ſhaken off the Roman yoake, and the French Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie was reeſtabliſhed, they began againe to take ſome care of their native Language, and Poetrie began to be in repute amongſt them, ſo farre that even Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152885:13"/>ordinarily addicted themſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. <hi>Chilperick</hi> the grand child of <hi>Clovis</hi> the Grand would ad unto the French Alphabet ſome Greeke letters, which he thought we ſhould want in our Orthographie, enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all Schoole-maſters within his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to make uſe of them in writing of French. <hi>Charlemaine</hi> writ in verſe the moſt memorable acts of his anceſtors, and himſelfe compoſed a French Grammer. <hi>Philip</hi> the renowned, and diverſe others of our Kings and Princes did alſo beautifie our native Language. But the Latin had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuch deepe root, that it alwaies pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, and hindered our Language from comming to its full perfection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis</hi> the Eleventh was the firſt that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually employed his power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the reſtauration and reeſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our native Language. For having reunited divers Provinces to the Crown, to make the Language alſo conformable, he cauſed divers diſpatches, which untill that time had been framed in corrupt Latine, to be afterwards written in French. And by this meanes this great King gave againe ſome luſtre and ſubſiſtence to our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, ſo that to him we may attribute the glory of having him, in ſome ſort, the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it ſeeing that by this his ordinance it began by little and little to be regulated,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152885:14"/>and come againe to ſome perfection, untill the raigne of <hi>Francis,</hi> who ſeconding his predeceſſors Royall intentions, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all pleadings to be in the Vulgar tongue, and judgements to be given there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, which had before been done in Latin. This great Prince alſo cauſed manie anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Authours to be tranſlated into French, and granted ſeverall priviledges and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, to Hiſtorians, Poets, and Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of his time.</p>
            <p>Our Language went on increaſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Great. For in their dayes a roſe many rare and ſublime underſtandings who pricked forward by a noble emulation and deſire of beautify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the French tongue, invented many new words, and writ ſeverall admirable workes: the chiefe whereof were <hi>Amiet, Ronſard, Baif, Du Bellay, Iodellus,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others, who having written all much about one time, might be ſaid to have brought our Language to a moſt high point of perfection. But doe what theſe great Princes could, they hardly freed it from its Parbariſmes, it was ſo confuſed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termingled with corrupt Latine, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe other tongues. His Majeſty hath found out the true, and hitherto concealed way, to regulate it in all its parts, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152885:14"/>it to a perfect accompliſhment, by the good advice &amp; known wiſedome of your Eminency, in founding the French Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and filling it with men of eminent and refined learning, the choiſe wits of the Kingdome, who diſcreetly omit and cut off unprofitable and ſuperfluous words, wiſely adding whatſoever is wanting in our Language for the happy expreſſing of our thoughts, baniſhing all thoſe Gothick termes which were crept in amongſt us by the communion we had with thoſe Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne nations, preſerving and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their roome ſuch as wee had bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from politer and more civilized people; ſo that our ſpeech is daily beautifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, our Authors write more without fault, our Lawyers grow more eloquent, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves in rhetoricall and fluent phraſes, our Provinces are purged of their ſeverall Dialects, which hindered their commerce, being hardly able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand one another without interprerers.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to tell your Eminency that for the perfecting of this great work, nothing was ſo neceſſary as the ſetling of an Academie in this Kingdome, in which both the native and forraigne gentry might learne Sciences in our mother tongue. This being an infallible meanes to reforme the Language even in the remoteſt Provinces,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152885:15"/>and reduce the whole nation to an unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of ſpeech and Dialect, to make our Language famous in ſtrange countries, cauſing all the ſubjects of this Kingdome to obſerve the rules and precepts of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademy. For Sir, we reade in Hiſtories that there be foure principall waies, to bring languages to a full perfection, amplifie, and immortalize them.</p>
            <p>The firſt is by Armes, when the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer binds the vanquiſhed to ſpeake his Language, either by planting colonies in it; or by cauſing all publick acts and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patces to be ſet downe and framed in that ſpeech which they intend to bring in. The greateſt marke of Soveraintie is to force conquered nations to alter their Idiom: and the laſt King of the antient <hi>Hetrurians,</hi> yeilded to all conditions which the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Romans would impoſe upon him, but onely to that of admitting the Latine tongue within his dominions. This was the meanes by which the Romans made a great part of the world ſpeake Latine, the Goths and Arabians introduced their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage within the bounds of the Roman Empire, and whereby the Turkes have ſo far extended their ſpeech. And this way is reſerved for your Eminency to advance, by making our armies victorious, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging the bounds of our Monarchie.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152885:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The ſecond meanes is, tranſlation of writers, whereby we change and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form into our own Language, the rare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and rich conceipts of other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; making them ſpeak ſuch an idiom as they never underſtood. For which cauſe <hi>Ptolomie</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi> filled up that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Librarie with ſeven hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Manuſcripts, the greateſt part wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were tranſlated out of other Tongues into Greek, and bought at ſo high a rate the verſion of the Septuagint. By meanes of tranſlation alſo did <hi>Aristotle</hi> write thoſe exquiſite Politicks (whereof ſome fragments onely remain to us) having the ſeverall ſorts of Governments of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the World brought unto him in writing; <hi>Alexander</hi> having ſent Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors every where, on purpoſe to extract the beſt out of each Countries Lawes, to have a perpect Politie framed thereby, which ſhould be inviolably obſerved within all his Dominions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans,</hi> following this great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch's example, ſent ſome of the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enteſt men of their Common-wealth into <hi>Greece,</hi> to tranſlate the beſt of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Lawes, out of which extracts, they fram'd their Law of the twelve Tables, called <hi>Lex duodecim tabularum,</hi> which was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſpring and foundation of all the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152885:16"/>
               <hi>Roman</hi> Lawes. And at their returne from <hi>Athens,</hi> their ordinary employment was, to tranſlate into Latine the moſt remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things which they found written in the Greek tongue. And amongſt the reſt <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> (as zealous in the beautifying of his native language, as of the maintaining of his Countries liberty) invented ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite termes for Morall Philoſophy, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all his works which are extant therein, are as ſo many of his Maſterpeeces. Some, to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much affected to the Greek tongue, would have diverted him from his intentions; but he rejecting their counſell, went happily on in his deſign, &amp;, had he not been prevented by a violent death, was reſolved to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the whole courſe of Philoſophie out of Greek into Latine, as he promiſeth in his ſecond Book <hi>de Divinatione,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeveral places. His death was one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the greateſt misfortunes that ever befell, not onely the Common-wealth of <hi>Rome,</hi> but ſince that allſo, all the States of Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endome; For ſince that great man, neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> durſt any undertake ſo great a work, and conſequently the Latine tongue hath wanted the pure termes of arts and ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces For though <hi>Boetius,</hi> upon the decaying of the Latine tongue, did attempt to tranſlate the courſe of Philoſophie, it was neither followed, nor taught. And thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152885:16"/>tranſlators as have undertaken any ſuch thing ſince the firſt foundation of our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, finding no proper Philoſophicall termes in any Latine Authors, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to frame new ones, ſo improper, barbarous, and remote from that primitive elegancie, that they would ſcarce have been underſtood by the antient <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Arabians</hi> uſed the ſame meanes, and there are even in theſe daies extant diverſe Greek Authors, yea, even ſome books of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tranſlated into the <hi>Arabick</hi> tongue, which are not to be had, neither in their own Originall, nor yet in Latine; which bookes the Eſtates of the united Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, great lovers and promoters of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are now cauſing to be tranſlated out of <hi>Arabick</hi> into Latine.</p>
            <p>And this meanes belongs properly to thoſe who are of the <hi>French</hi> Academie; it is a commendable kind of work, which may be performed in a ſtudy at conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient houres. And ſeeing they are ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly skilled in forreign Languages, that they can prudently thereby regulate, and enrich ours; we do hope and expect from this honorable company, faithfull tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the beſt books antiquity hath left us; which they may perform as a recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in their vacant houres, to ſolace them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152885:17"/>after their ſerious employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in producing and inventing new and elegant words and expreſſions.</p>
            <p>The third meanes is Grammar, by which we learn to decline and conjugate, read, and pronounce in all places, in one manner. And for this end, <hi>Ariſtotle, Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Aristophanes, Apollodorus, Ariſtarchus, Chryſippus, Cicero, Caeſar, Varro, Quintilian, Donatus, Priſcian, Charlemaine,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great perſons of both Nations have written ſo carefully thereof. The <hi>Roman</hi> did for that end erect two and twenty pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſchooles in <hi>Rome,</hi> and many more in their ſeverall Provinces, to inſtruct their children, and bring them up in an uniform pronunciation. Though they had not in thoſe daies any Colledges founded for Sciences, but Greek teachers onely made uſe of in private houſes, to teach them Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in the Greek language.</p>
            <p>And if <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt had well be thought himſelf, and firſt endeavoured to have an uniformity of language in all his Dominions, and had to that end founded French Grammer-ſch ooles in ſeverall Cities of his Kingdome; he had ſaved much of that vaſt expence which he was a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in erecting of ſo many Colledges for the <hi>Hebrew, Greek, Arabian,</hi> &amp; <hi>Latine</hi> tongues and there had not been at this time ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152885:17"/>ſeverall ſorts of ſpeeches, in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but all would have ſpoken after one manner.</p>
            <p>But the moſt certain, and powerfull meanes to regulate Languages, and make them laſting and univerſal, is to make them interpreters of Sciences, which are no ſooner brought into a Nationall Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, but they grace it with all neceſſary ornaments, and make it every way com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. By their meanes, the <hi>Egyptian, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Arabian</hi> tongues have obtained ſo much credit in the world; and learned Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have made all the Earth ſpeake their particular and Mother Languages. Their workes have croſſed the Seas, and when they have been baniſhed out of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, they have found courteous entertainment amongſt forreign Nations. The authority of Sciences hath given the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Languages their paſſe to travell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our parts. Conquerors can extend their Languages no further then the bounds of their Conqueſts, nor can they make them laſt there any longer then their own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Translators and Grammarians have alſo in ſome manner their bounds. Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces onely enjoy the priviledge and prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of making anguages immortall, and extending them beyond the bounds of thoſe Kingdomes in which they had their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152885:18"/>origine: So that when they are dead in their own naturall Country where they were firſt ſpoken, they ſurvive amongſt other Nations, or at leaſt find an honorable tomb in the memory of the learned'ſt and wiſeſt men.</p>
            <p>Want of this laſt meanes, hath been the cauſe that our French tongue hath remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed barren and unpoliſht, without rule and order within the Kingdom, reſtrained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it, and for a long time unknown to ſtrangers. It wants not all diſpoſitions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired for the perfecting of it, if it were but well followed; for queſtionleſſe all Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages are of themſelves equally able to expreſſe their thoughts: and if any one hath a prerogative above the other, it muſt be attributed onely to the labour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry of the moſt excellent men of each Nation. When <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Demoſthenes, Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Virgil, Boccace</hi> and <hi>Petrarch, Grenada</hi> and <hi>Lopezde Vega, Amiot</hi> and <hi>Ron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſard,</hi> framed a deſign to write in their own Languages, they were then but in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie, and yet theſe famous Perſons brought them almoſt to the height of their accompliſhment. Whence we may inferre, that thoſe famous and ſtately Languages, which antiquity hath ſo much admired, were in their beginning weak and abject; they have in time been brought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152885:18"/>by the care and induſtry of wiſe and learned men, who have laboured to find out as many names, as there were things, wherein conſiſts the eſſence and perfection of Languages; whereas hitherto we have ſervilely beſtowed our times and ſtudies to the refining and reſtoring of Forreign and obſolet Languages, unfortunately neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our own. Whence it proceeds, that we have not found needfull and fitting words and terms to expreſſe our ſelves; and, to our ſhame and ignominie, wee can not name many things in French, for which we have names both in Greek and Latine; whereas other Nations, that have not known thoſe forreign and obſolet Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, or at leaſt have made no uſe of them in diſcourſe, have found out moralls enough of their own, to expreſſe their thoughts and Knowledges.</p>
            <p>As ſoone as children become rationall, and have attained to ſuch an age that they can ſpeake well and correct thoſe childiſh utterances which they had gotten from nurſes in ſtead of making them eloquent in their language, they teach them Greeke and Latine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> contemning the French; ſo that when they forſake the Colleges, wherein they have ſpent the prime of their youth, they ſeeme to be ſtrangers in their owne countrie, and retaine the ill tones,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152885:19"/>and unſavory pronunciations of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall provinces, which afterwards they can never leave, ſo that after fifteene or twenty yeares ſtudy, they ſpeake like the vulgar and common ſort of people, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver become eloquent in the French tongue, whatſoe ver profeſſion they follow.</p>
            <p>The ſelfe ſame thing is the reaſon why it is impoſſible for us to become truely lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, becauſe that to be right Philoſophers we muſt of neceſsity doe as they did in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times, namely, make uſe of a popular uſuall and nationall mother tougue. For though the names w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> we learne even from the breaſt, be not more ſignificant then the other, yet becauſe that long cuſtome hath made them familiar unto us, and as it were naturall, the Ideas or images of the names, and of the things inſinuating themſelves into us joyntly at one time, the former through the eares, and the latter through the eyes, and are joyned and inſeparablie vnited in our memory, and knit together by ſo perfect a ſympathy and ſtrict cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that it is impoſsible to thinke upon the one without remembring the other; and whilſt the love of theſe two Ideas is reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall, and they are faithfull to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they ingender knowledge and polite ſpeech in our mindes; but if either of them violates the I awes of this ſacred union,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152885:19"/>&amp; ſuffers it ſelf to be tranſported to illegal Objects; they produce nothing but barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm &amp; confuſion. Now this miſ-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding happeneth chiefly two waies, either when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> underſtanding abandoning the conſideration of faire and ſolid truth, ſeeks only after frivolous &amp; chimericall things; or when it addicts it ſelf to ſtrange languages which are but ſervants; &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temns his mother tongue which is his true ſpouſe, and imitates <hi>Polygamie</hi> which is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar to ſome Nations where Concubines are preferred before the Lawfull Wife. Which cannot chuſe but be very prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to diſcourſe, becauſe that on the one ſide, the images of thoſe things which are not, can engender in our minds nothing but falſe &amp; ſpuirous notions, ſuch as blind men have of colours, of which they know on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the name: &amp; on the other ſide, the idea of one only thing comming to unite it ſelf in the memory to the Ideas and images of ſo many ſtrange &amp; differing words, alters, &amp; confounds not only the ſpecies of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue, but alſo breeds ſo great a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion in the ſpecies of other languages, that in ſtead of ſtirring up the Image of a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> word, and uttering of it, oftentimes it ſtirrs up and utters ſome <hi>Italian</hi> or <hi>French</hi> words: &amp; thence it comes that thoſe who have learn'd many languages, cannot chuſe ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times but confound &amp; mix the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together.</p>
            <p>The Ideas of things, and of names, have
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152885:20"/>been freely beſtowed upon us at one time, the former by nature, and the latter by our nurſes, to make us capable of diſcourſe and communication; but be cauſe the Ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as of names commonly make not ſo deepe an impreſſion in us, as the Ideas of things; we ought to practiſe them care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully from our tender age, and ſtrengthen them in ſuch ſort by frequent repetition; that the memorie may not labour more in preſerving and uttering them, then it doth in conceiving the Ideas of things; otherwiſe we ſhall never obtain in the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of well ſpeaking, but ſhall ſtill be troubled with conceiving, and not have power to bring forth; which is one of the greateſt diſaſters and troubles that can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall our mindes. And to make it appear, that we may longer and eaſier remember the ſpecies of things then the names of them, we find by experience, that every man is oftentimes troubled to remember ſome names which he hath almoſt daily uttered, and yet ſhall not eaſily forget the ſpecies of a thing which he hath once or twice attentively marked and obſerved. Finally experience teacheth us, that he tongue and the thought doe alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſomewhat of the quality of the cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate: Which is the cauſe that a <hi>Greek,</hi> or <hi>Italian</hi> thought, that hath alwaies even
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152885:20"/>from its infancy been brought up and nouriſhed with its own Country lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as with a ſiſter; hath more relation and conformity to, and with it, then with any other, and that a Science which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts all in word and thought, is never naturall, nor can enter or take any deep root in the ſpirit, unleſſe it be taught in the mother tongue. That is the reaſon, why when we ſpeak <hi>French,</hi> our words come from us eaſilie, and a polite phraſe is utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by us as ſudainly as a well conceived thought; whereas in a <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Latin</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, wee muſt continually attend to the choice of terms, ſtudying upon every word we utter, which turmoiles our mind, and hinders it from employing it ſelfe with full liberty in the indagation of a truth; which is alſo the cauſe that we do not eaſilie forget our Mother tongue; whereas ſtrange languages are as ſoone blotted out of our memories, as we give over the uſe of them; and the profeſſors thereof no ſooner diſcontinue the practiſe, but they loſe that habit which they had obtained with ſo much labour, and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie.</p>
            <p>Ever fince the Creation of the World, untill about the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, all the Nations of the Earth, <hi>Gaules, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyſtians, Perſians,</hi> and <hi>Grecians</hi> taught Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152885:21"/>in Nationall and Mother tongues, and if they did borrow any help of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Languages, they were ſuch as were ſtill in uſe, and had their courſe among the learned, who were conſulted with as ſo many Oracles; and beſides, it was but only untill ſuch time that their owne Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage was brought to perfection, and they had invented termes enough for Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. But this great <hi>Bruce,</hi> being choſen King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> abſolute in a great part of <hi>Europe,</hi> and conſidering that the Language was extreamly corrupted in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, through the incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and eſpcially in theſe <hi>Western</hi> parts; ſo that it was almoſt impoſſible to regulate it, and in it to teach Sciences (which he ſavoured as much as any Monarch in the World) he judged it more expedient at that time to reeſtabliſh the Latin tongue every where, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it to its pureneſſe, then to refine and bring in uſe that Latin which was uſuall in his time. To this end he ſet up Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, cauſed all Pleas, and acts to be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſet down in Latin. Queſtionleſſe nis intentions were commendable, and Noble; yet they had no proſperous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe: For he ſuppreſſed a certaine mixt Language, which was then popular, and might eaſily have been made perfect and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152885:21"/>compleat; and yet did not revive the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <hi>Roman</hi> tongue which was quite dead and extinguiſhed. Which occaſioned a mighty diſorder, becauſe that out of the corruption of one Language, there were three framed, which in a ſmall time grew ſo different one from another, that they could not be underſtood, but onely by thoſe who particularly profeſſed them. For then the <hi>French, Spaniſh,</hi> and <hi>Italian Grammarians</hi> ſtudied nothing but the pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Language, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers the groſſe vulgar and new invented Latin, and the common people wanting rules and inſtructions touching the mixt Language, from thoſe who could ſpeake well in it, could not of themſelves turne the barbarous forraigne words into La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, which of it ſelfe is difficult enough; and were forced to fly for reliefe to thy Subſtantive and auxiliarie Verbes. And by this meanes were framed in <hi>France, Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> a kind of baſtard Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which are nothing but a kind of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Latin. Philoſophie is very naturall to man; and rareſt wits have in all ages been curious in the ſearch of truth; which we might more clearly have perceived by their works, had they not been loſt by the corruption of Languages, deluges, firings, warrs, and tranſmigrations
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152885:22"/>of Nations. Philoſophie is the worthieſt Object of our admiration, and one of the rareſt preſents Heaven hath beſtowed upon us; by its meanes we are raiſed, and elevated to the knowledge of divine things, we peretrate into the ſecrets of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; wee regulate our manner of living, and entertaine humane ſociety; and yet now it is made odious unto us, thorow the difficulty of thoſe Languages which are inſtrumentall to her, and the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm of new invented termes. The light of mens underſtandings ſeemes to be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and yet certainly reaſon doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate. All ages produce gallant men, and moſt acute wits, who ought to be more learned then thoſe who lived in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, having this advantage, to have the uſe of all their inventions, and time daily diſcloſing ſome new experiment. Is it not a great eaſe unto us in theſe daies to have <hi>Euclide</hi>'s Elements ſo carefully ſet forth, <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Philoſophy ſo ſolidly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his Maximes ſo judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ordered, &amp; ſo many other rare and excellent workes, which loſt, could never have been made good again? How comes it then, that we are not as learned as they were in thoſe daves, and have not in theſe latter Ages ſuch men as <hi>Hippocrates, Ariſtotle, Euclide, Archimedes, Diophantus,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152885:22"/>Tullie, Plutarch,</hi> and <hi>Seneca?</hi> What is the reaſon that Philoſophie ſtill degenerates, and that ſo many ſtudious braines who watch continually, and burn of a deſire to learn, can not ſo much as adde one degree of perfection to Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, nor yet exquiſitely tread thoſe paths in which they formerly walked? Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſs it is, becauſe we do not as thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and well adviſed people did, who brought their Children directly to learne Sciences when they were but ſeven or eight yeares of age, and never put them to fruitleſſe ſtudies of unuſed and ſtrange Languages. They reaſoned fluently without any trouble; whereas now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe ſeven or eight hundred yeares, we employ the flower of our age, in which wee might make moſt proficiencie in our ſtudies, towards obtaining of Sciences in a kind of apprentice-ſhip, in ſeeking to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore thoſe obſolete Languages; ſetting more by a few Grammaticall obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Etymologies of words, then Mathematicall Demonſtrations, or Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims of Philoſophie.</p>
            <p>Yet queſtionleſſe we ſee this apprentice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which we are tied to in atta ining of theſe aboliſhed Languages, is bevond compariſon more tedious and hard, then all morall and natural Sciences.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152885:23"/>How watchfull, ſtudious, and turmoiled muſt we be before we can attain, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the polite ſpeaking, but even to a rough underſtanding of the Greek or Latin tongue? Our minds, and all the faculties of our ſoules, ſuffer a thouſand torments in the compaſſing of it; in ſo much that a free ſpirit, and a Noble Genius, can hardly captivate it ſelf to ſo many rudiments of Grammer, ſo many particles and frivolous obſervations; it daſhes and dulls it ſelf, and in the end ſhakes off this cumberſome yoak, and by that meanes it happens oftentimes to the great dammage of the publick good, that the French Nobilitie, endowed with moſt rare naturall faculties, being not able to ſubject it ſelf to ſuch an intricate ſtudy, conceives a mortall hatred againſt all manner of learning, which of it ſelfe is a thing ſo rare, and to which they have ſo great a naturall inclination.</p>
            <p>This is the reaſon that <hi>Northern</hi> Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who have but a meane and dull ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, do more willingly apply themſelves to the learning of Languages, employ their whole time therein, and are not tired with this bondage and ſervitude; whereas the <hi>Southern,</hi> abhorring ſo fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a labour, unworthy of a high and lofty mind, addict themſelves wholly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152885:23"/>to Sciences, and meditation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Triſmegiſtus,</hi> who is accounted to have been the founder of Sciences, a great King, Prieſt, and Philoſopher, made ſo little eſteem of the Greek tongue, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Egyptian, that he was even afraid leaſt thoſe rare workes which he had compiled concerning all Divine and humane Sciences, ſhould be tranſlated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Language. The <hi>Grecians,</hi> having learned from the <hi>Egyptians</hi> to cheriſh and refine their own Language, did ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn all others, that they called them <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians.</hi> And thereupon <hi>Plutarch</hi> cared not for learning of the Latin tongue; though it was in his time moſt flouriſhing, and he lived in <hi>Traian's</hi> Court, where it was moſt purely ſpoken, and that he had undertaken the writing of the <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the honour of <hi>Africk,</hi> and of the Church, who eaſilie could comprehend and penetrate into any thing; complaines in diverſe places, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in his Confeſſions, of the difficulty he found in learning the Greek tongue by precepts; and averreth that it cannot be inculcated into the memory, without rough threatnings, and ſevere correct ons, which dulls the courage of a childe, and diſtracts his Sences. He ſaith that alſo he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152885:24"/>found more diſtaſt then pleaſure in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Homer</hi> himſelf, though it was ſo ful of varieties, and recreative and pleaſant fictions: and that contrariwiſe he lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Latin tongue in ſporting among women and children, though it was no more naturall to him then the Greek, becauſe he was ſent to learn it in a City of <hi>Africk,</hi> which was a <hi>Roman</hi> Colonie, and where they ordinarilſe did ſpeake Latin.</p>
            <p>We have in theſe daies farre greater oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to complain; they put us in priſon, and torment us in Colledges for the ſpace often or twelve yeares, to learne Preterits, Supines, Syntaxes, Heteroclites, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomala, which, one may in truth ſay, are but the excrements, and impurities of an irregular, and imperfect Language. For in Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> daies, there was yet ſome pretence and colour for the learning of Latin and Greek, which was nationall and popular in a great part of the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> but now why ſhould we in vaine trouble our ſelves to revive obſolet Languages, which ſerve no longer for any commerce? The learnedſt amongſt the <hi>Grecians,</hi> in former times, were wont to blame the <hi>Grammarians,</hi> who beſtowed ſo much time in teaching the Grammer, and the Mother tongue, to the prejudice of Sciences; But
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152885:24"/>what would they ſay, I pray you, if they ſaw now the diſorders of our ſchoole? would they not have farre greater occs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to complain of the length of the bondage we endure in learning of ſtrange languages; which robbs us of the beſt time we have to attain to learning? All Languages ought to be learned by pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice, and not by precepts: and wee finde by experience, that the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers,</hi> which come to dwell in <hi>France</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, cauſe their Language to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their own private families, and their children are brought up in it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violence or precepts. Nations frame e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day amongſt themſelves new ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches naturally; and as it were unawares: and yet theſe numberleſs Greek and Latin teachers cannot in ſeven or eight hundred yeares make theſe Languages familiar in any Colledge, nor bring youth to ſpeake them naturally: But yet wee neede not marvell, if Languages follow the order of Generations, of which we never ſee the beginning, nor ending; and as we can not raiſe them up again to their ſpring and origine, ſo it is impoſſible to hinder them from deſcending, and wearing away.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Egyptians</hi> reproved the <hi>Grecians,</hi> who came to ſtudie amongſt them, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152885:25"/>they remaine in continuall infancie all their life time, without Knowledge or diſcourſe: becauſe they did not profit by their inſtructions, and could not all under one, learne a forraign Language, though it were uſuall both in the Maſters and the Schollers mouthes, and apprehend the Myſteries of their Doctrines. But as ſoone as the <hi>Grecians</hi> began to learne and teach Philoſophie in their own proper and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall tongue, they ſoon went beyond the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who were their maſters, in all manner of learning: and afterward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to contemn all other Languages, holding the <hi>Romans, Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginians</hi> for barbarous Nations, becauſe they had not Sciences in their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Idioms. Whereas if they had ſtill learned Philoſophie in the <hi>Chaldean</hi> and <hi>Egyptian</hi> Languages, they had continued in their infancy for ever.</p>
            <p>By this meanes, all thoſe Nations which ſtudied Philoſophie in their own mother tongue, became betimes ſolid in learning, and eloquent, and have left behind them ſolid and eloquent workes. <hi>Galen</hi> ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his own tongue, happily attained to perfection, and was both a Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician, a Philoſopher, and a Phyſician in fifteen or ſixteen yeares, as well as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe others of his time: and contrariwiſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152885:25"/>thoſe Nations which taught, and do teach in obſolet Languages, never taſte the ſweet of Sciences, the very entrance thereinto ſeeming to them craggy and ine acceſlible: and if at laſt they attaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereunto, it is with infinite labour; and although they be learned, yet are they barbarous in their manners, actions, and words. How many learned men are there amongſt us that cannot ſpeak French, and when they ſhould come to the chaire to read, or the barre to plead, they wonder they muſt again the ſecond time learne their Grammar; which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible for them to doe, becauſe their memory faileth them, and they have gotten ſuch a continuall habit of their evill Provinciall accent, and termes which are notuſuall in Court, nor will paſſe in gentile companies. For the ſame was the reaſon, why, whileſt they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and preached in Latin here in <hi>France,</hi> the pulpets, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rres ſwarmed with groſſe, ignorant, and barbarous perſons; But as ſoon as they began to ſpeak French, we have had ſuch rare Preachers and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Advocates, that the French elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, which may yet be ſtiled to be but in its infancie, may conteſt either with Greek or Latin.</p>
            <p>Advocates indeed had more reaſon
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152885:26"/>then any others, to retaine, and preſerve the uſe of the Latin tongue, becauſe moſt of our Lawes are derived from it; the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Law was compiled in it in exquiſite termes, and it hath been ſo carefully po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and refined by the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate, both in civill and criminall matters, that one may ſay, it was the firſt and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſchoole of eloquence that ever was; and that the Greek, which hath ſo many other excellencies, is in this point inferiour to it, and hath been forced in matters of Law to borrow many Latin words, and cloth them in a Greek habit. Yer they were the firſt, who thorow a generous deſire to ſerve their Country, and honour their Nation, did caſt off the Latin, our Language being indebted to them for its politeneſſe and elegancie; and I admire that this their rare example, ſeconded with ſuch a happy ſucceſſe, hath not obliged Philoſophers, Mathem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>icians, and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians to forſake their barbarous termes, and remnants of Latin, to joyn with the Lawyers in the compleating of their own mother tongue.</p>
            <p>Man is born for Sciences, whereof he hath the ſeed within himſelf; and to the end that he may diſcourſe in his infancie, and loſe no time, nature, as ſoone as hee comes out of his cradle, gratifies him
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152885:26"/>with meanes neceſlary for him to become learned, cauſing him to ſuck and draw his own native tongue together with his nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes milke, when he is not yet capable of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing elſe, that he may enter into his Philoſophie, as ſoon as he hath the very firſt degree of reaſon. And that our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon mother Nature hath not deſtinated us to learn languages, we may perceive by this, that the older we grow, the more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit we are for the attaining of them; and a man who is come to a perfect and mature age, ſhall labour more to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain one Language, then a child in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning three or four ſeverall ones. Beſides, Sciences trouble not the mind as Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges doe; and the more a man learne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, the apter he is to learn; Sciences having ſuch a relation to one another, and being ſo linked together, that they lend mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all aſſiſtance to one another; they are ſiſters which live in perfect unitie, without any miſunderſtanding, finding a joint ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation in our mind, as it were in their fathers houſe, which conceiving every where objects of the ſame kind, needs but one Image to comprehend all thoſe things which are of the ſame nature. Wheras the Memorie, by reaſon of the diverſity of Languages, is ſaine to burthen itſelf with an infinite number of ſpecificall nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152885:27"/>which trouble one another, and make a horrible confuſion in that facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And furthermore we find by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that thoſe who have many Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, are never ſo fitting for ſublime meditations, and deep diſcourſes: and that to be a ſound Philoſopher, it is better to ſpeak but one, and have the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at libertie, and free from the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricacie of ſtrange words.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Egyptian, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Arabian</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, conſidering that Nature, repleat both with goodneſſe, and wiſdom, did bring up children all at once to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge both of names, and things, and that ſhe did ſuggeſt unto u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> words, according as she inſpired us with thoughts; did alſo at the ſame time reſpect as well the one as the other, and were equally carefull of inſtructing children in well ſpeaking, and in doctrine; As ſoon as the light of reaſon began to appear, they ſowed into the memory as in a fruitful ſoil, the ſeeds and principles of Knowledge, which ſerved for a guide and conduct of their life; ſo that good and wholſome Maxims taking deep root in the underſtanding, did in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of time fructifie, and increaſe there: whereby former ages brought forth ſuch men as poſterity admired, and whoſe very names were honoured and reſpected.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152885:27"/>
            <p>But now, in ſtead of beſtowing our ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der age in things which might edifie youth, we caſt it into the briars of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, and ſuch tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ubleſome difficulties, as dull the acuteneſſe of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: they oppreſſe the memory with the troubleſome ſtudie of obſolet Languages, the Knowledge of which is many times fruitleſſe, and to no purpoſe eſpecially for ſuch as doe not make a profeſſion of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or ſpeaking Greek and Latine. That time might be employed farre better in the refining of our own Language, and the ſearch of truth: and queſtionleſſe the <hi>French,</hi> who are endowed with ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and rare naturall gifts, would quickly become, as they were in the <hi>Druides</hi> times, the moſt learned and eloquent in the World, and Philoſophie would once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain flouriſh amongſt us. Is it not a ſhame, that through neglect of our owne language, we ſhould ſpeak many things in Greek and Latin which wee might as well expreſſe in our mother tongue? Is not this a making our ſelves ſtrangers in our own Country, and never behold learning but in borrowed robes?</p>
            <p>One might object, that children are not capable of Sciences, and that ſtudying of them is too ſerious and important an employment for them. Yet experience
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152885:28"/>teacheth us the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary; &amp; <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf in his <hi>Politicks</hi> ſaith, that children are cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of learning Philoſophie at ſeven or eight yeares of age, becauſe they begin then to be capable of reaſon, their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is vivid, and hot, their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie tender, and apt to receive any good impreſſion: and it is farr eaſier for them to apprehend Reaſons, whereof they have the principles within themſelves then the Rudiments of Grammer, which are fruitleſs bloſſoms, and to which they have no naturall diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>This error hath by little and little crept into the minds of men, becauſe they have not conſidered that there are two ſorts of Sciences, namely of Invention, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline. As for the firſt, children indeed are not capable of them, and even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men none can attaine thereunto, unleſſe they be ſublimed wits, and ſpirits fitted to invent new things: they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaſours of an extraordinary Genius, or a continual ſtudy of 20. or 30. years, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with long and profound meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſolitarie reflections, which at laſt diſcover unto us ſome particular lights. And ſuch wits deſerve even to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; they are the honour of mankind, and raiſe it up to a kinde of divinity. As for the Sciences of Diſcipline, or diſpoſition,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152885:28"/>they are not of the ſame nature: all ſuch as have any memory, even women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are capable thereof; they are but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterations of what hath been ſaid before, which may be eaſily apprehended, when they are explained and expounded; yet are they ſeeds of the high Science of Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when they are ſown in a fruitfull, ſublimed, and extraordinary underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Therefore even the Northerne dull Nations are capable of knowing, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending what hath beene written and experimented by others, becauſe they have good memories, which in ſome manner ſupplie their default of Invention. And the Southerne people being more Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, having ſought out the truth in Ancient writers, are fitter through their acuteneſſe to diſcover new inventions. Wherein we may admire divine providence, which having made all men rationall, guides them ſeverall waies to one end, giving the one a more lively judgment, and the others a more happie memorie. Why ſhould then that time, which is ordained for ſciences, be ſo ill employed in an apprentiſhip to learne grammatical obſervations and precepts, far harder and more difficult then the language it ſelf? why ſhould we ſpend ten or twelve yeares in ſtudying Greek and Latine, to make uſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afterwards but one year or
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152885:29"/>two in the ſtudie of Philoſophie? Is it not an uniuſt and inſufferable thing, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the moſt pretious time of our life, and moſt fitting to learne ſciences, namely from ſeven or eight, to eighten or twenty yeares of age, in learning of the grammer &amp; ſome bookes of humanitie, with intollerable trouble and labour, then, when youths begin to incline to diſſoluteneſſe, and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauches, gaming, hunting, and travelling, they are put to Logick, in which they muſt againe begin to learne a new kind of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, ſo barbarous and obſcure, that it ſeems to have been invented, onely to make Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences odious, and diſtaſtfull. And by this means, in ſtead of prolonging the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries time of ſtudying, they are forced ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruply to cut it off; their imployments cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to ſtate affaires, ſo that what they have not learned at fifteen or ſixteen yeares of age, they muſt be ignorant of all the dayes of their lives, to the great dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and prejudice of the ſtate.</p>
            <p>And thus through the difficulty &amp; tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of learning Greek &amp; Latine, our great ones are fruſtrate of their rudiments of Philoſophie, which is one of the greateſt miſhaps that can befall a State. For there are but very few that can attain to the fight of the luſtre of Sciences thorough ſo much miſt and darkeneſſe: ſublime &amp; moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152885:29"/>underſtandings onely can comprehend all things, without any intricacy or confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And it is a miraculous thing how a perfect knowledge of languages, joyned with deep learning (which ordinarily make a man penſive, ſolitarie, and moſt fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for a private life) can conſiſt in your Eminency, together with ſuch cleareneſſe of ſpirit, grave carriage, majeſtick and bewitching entertainement, which doth charme and captivate mens hearts unto you; and the knowledge of all theſe things, hath furniſhed and fittingly diſpoſed you to become the moſt abſolute States-man that ever was in <hi>France.</hi> So that in you ſir is verified that Maxime which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſets down, namely, that Policie is the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris and Queen of all other Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; becauſe ſhe it is that regulates their functions, and applies them to the good of the publick. And now <hi>France</hi> findes by experience, to its honour and glory, that Kingdomes never flouriſh and proſper better, then when prudent and learned men ſit at the ſterne of publick affaires. I muſt notwithſtanding confeſſe that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe and underſtanding people, have ſtudied in forraigne Languages, ſome have travelled into <hi>Egypt,</hi> to <hi>Marſeilles, Greece,</hi> and other countries famous for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and learned profeſſors; which have
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152885:30"/>lived and taught in them: but they were then naticnall Languages, and needfull for the learning of Sciences, and uſefull in the chiefeſt ports in the world, into which one could not travaile without them: And they were ſo farre from being difficult and hard to learne, that one could not almoſt avoyd nor ſhun the learning of them through daily converſation with the men, women and children of that country. But why do we now adaies without any neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity ſo much ſeeke after I anguages, that lie buried in Libraries as in their Sepulchers? Let us ſtirre up their aſhes as long as wee will, we ſhall never revive them: the frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and relicks which are left of them, are but ſo many ſhadowes, and defaced monuments. And ſometimes we turmoile our ſelves about them all our life time, and yet cannot attaine to the true Genius and pronunciation of them; in which, as the Greek oratour ſaith, conſiſts the ſpirit and ſoule of a language. Is not this I pray a kind of husbanding another mans land, letting our owne lie fallow?</p>
            <p>The Greekes did in former ages ſee the Aegyptians Language and Philoſophie fall to decay, and the <hi>Arabians,</hi> the <hi>Greekes;</hi> and yet thoſe politick nations never went about to ſupport, or re-eſtabliſh them: Yea contrariwiſe they ſought all meanes,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152885:30"/>utterly to aboliſh and ſuppreſſe them, to bring their own mother tongue into credit. Conſidering that it was no leſſe diſgrace for them to bee governed by forraigne tongues, then by forraigne armes and powers.</p>
            <p>Some teſtie Critick, or abſurd Polititian will peradventure ſay, that it is not fitting to lay open the myſteries of a Science, nor make them common. And that a Science is the more majeſtick and venerable, when it is obſcure and hidden from the common ſort of people. And therefore Aegyptians ſet down their Philoſophie in Hieroglyphicks; the firſt Greekes, and the antient Gauls in obſcure verſes! But this was an error, which great <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> both oppoſed, and reformed. For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> reduced all Sciences to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and treated of all things as an Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metician; <hi>Plato</hi> reaſoned of all naturall things as a Geometrician; <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> as an Aſtonomer, &amp; every ſect in ſome Enig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall and extravagant manner: This divine Genius of Nature ſpoke of every thing without any mixture, and in its own purity, phyſical matters as a Phyſick, of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, as a Politician, of Logick as a Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, of Metaphyſicks as a Divine, and ſo laid open the whole courſe of Philoſophy, diſperſing thoſe ſhadowes and Chimeras
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152885:31"/>made it obſcure, and darke. And indeed we ought to take the ſhorteſt, and neereſt way we can find, to conduct us to Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; for if we linger, or goe aſtray never ſo little, wee ſhall never come to an end of this brave journey, there are ſo many things to be known in this world. The volume which Nature gives us to reade o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is ſo large, ſhenath ſo many ſecrets hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in her breaſt, that we are ſo farre from attaining to the knowledge of all things, that the rareſt and moſt underſtanding men and witts have averred, that all that we know is nothing, in compariſon of things which are unknowne to us: and it may truely be ſaid, that the termes of Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and Arts are ſo particular, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar, and alien from an ordinarie Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, that they cannot be underſtood in any kind of ſpeech, but onely by ſuch as profeſſe the ſaid Arts, and Sciences. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, men are borne for knowledge, and it is a notable wrong done to them, to take away the means, and make the way there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto hard and difficult. The Schooles (as they were in former times in <hi>Aegypt Greece,</hi> and <hi>Arabia</hi>) ought to be open to all the world. In thoſe dayes children had fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed their ſtudie of Mathematicks, and Philoſophy at fourteene or fifteene years, before they were of age to undertake that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152885:31"/>profeſſion whereunto they were deſtinated for the reſidue of their life; which made them more capable and fitting for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick employments. For all the parts of philoſophy and Mathematicks are app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the neceſsity of living, and well-fare of Commonwealths. Logick cleares and ſtrengthens diſcourſe, giving a method and rule unto it. Morall Philoſophie governes and mitigates our paſſions, makes us good fathers of families, and good Citizens. Phyſick gives us the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and diſpoſeth us to be good Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians: The Mathematicks fit us for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires belonging either to war or peace, either in Mechanick or Liberall Arts, which are the grounds, and maintainers of Societies: But after we have conſumed all our youthfull dayes in learning of Greek and Latine, all this labour and watchfulneſſe ſtands us in no ſtead, but onely to reade ſome Greeke and Latine Authors, which is but an unprofitable curioſity for the party, and caſts us into a kind of droniſhneſſe, and diſables us from doing any thing elſe; ſo that thoſe who have ſo ſpent their time, are not capable of any profeſsion, and are but unprofitable Citizens, which can contribute nothing to the good of a Common-wealth, nor or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of a State.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152885:32"/>
            <p>So that many men who are not apt to learne Languages, or have not time to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelves therein, are fruſtrate of the fruites of Sciences, who might other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe become great perſons; if the ſaid Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences were taught in the vulgar or mother tongue; Whereof we have notable and famous examples in <hi>Simon</hi> of <hi>Athens, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemon,</hi> and <hi>Protagoras,</hi> who comming by chance into the Schooles of <hi>Socrates, Ariſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes,</hi> and <hi>Xenocrates</hi> were ſo feelingly touched, and powerfully edified by their Doctrine, that they preſently reſolved to forſake thoſe ſordid trades in which they had ſpent the greateſt part of their lives, and reforming their behaviours, addicted themſelves wholy to Philoſophie and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
            <p>If Philoſophie had no other interpreter but the Latine tongue, we ſhould indeed adheare, and apply our ſelves to that, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could we any way avoyd the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, ſeeing that without it we could not attaine to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hiloſophie. But all I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages are fitting for it, and ſubſervient to it: And though it be contrarie to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinion, we may ſay and a verr, that the Latine is extremely defective in that particular; becauſe it appeares, that in its moſt flouriſhing time, the termes for Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences were not known in <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152885:32"/>which were invented ſince, ſavour not of the Genius of pure Latine, and could not outlive a life leſſe Language.</p>
            <p>The Latine as well as other Languages hath been ſubject to mixture and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and hath not long remained in one ſtate, as divers learned Authours have written. We may obſerve in it five ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Idiomes, or kindes of Language. Namely, the firſt, and Ancient; the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, the <hi>Roman,</hi> the Mixt, and the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard. The Ancient, which the firſt and primitive people of <hi>Italie</hi> uſed, wherein ſome obſolet verſes were extant in <hi>Varroes</hi> time, though hardly underſtood, flouriſhed under <hi>Ianus</hi> and <hi>Saturne.</hi> The Latin, which the Latins uſed, was ſpoken under the raignes of the <hi>Tuscan</hi> Kings, and in that Language were written the <hi>Decemvires</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, the holy and ſacred lawes, and the publique Edicts. The Roman, which ſetes downe the Roman Hiſtories, and the Civill Law, began immediately after the Kings were expelled, and was refined by the Poets, <hi>Plautus, Nevius, Pacuvius, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Virgil, Ovid.</hi> and <hi>Horace;</hi> amongſt Oratours and Hiſtoriographers, by <hi>Cato, Hortenſius, Cicero, Caeſar, Saluſt,</hi> and <hi>Livie.</hi> The Mixt began with the increaſe of the Empire, and was in Eſteeme under the Empercurs, who admitting divers nations
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152885:33"/>to the right of being Roman Citizens, &amp; to citie honours, were thereby conſtrained to admit alſo of a mixture of feverall barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous words; by which meanes the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man vertue began to degenerate, and by little and little, with its liberty, loſt the purity of its Language. Finally, the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, and Spurious Latine which hath la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted from the diſsipation of the Empire to this time, every day receding more and more from its primitive pureneſſe, at laſt was divided into the Italian, Spaniſh, French, and ſeverall other tongues.</p>
            <p>As for the laſt, and the three firſt, thoſe who are well read in Hiſtories know they never had the termes of Sciences, the fourth onely, namely the Mixt had that priviledge towards its declining, and it was not long a nationall Language, nor had not age or time enough to be brought to the height of its perfections. And now Latin is made uſe of but only in ſome parts of Europe where it is ſo ſubjeſt to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt pronu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ciation of ſeverall Nations, that a French man can hardly underſtand a Germans Latine, nor an Italian an Iriſh mans, &amp;c. And beſides the Latine tongue is now ſo defective, that we can hardly expreſſe our ſelves in it, the tearmes of all Arts and Sciences being ſo farre altered, hat they have no relation to the Language
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152885:33"/>as was in former times. And laſtly, the knowledge of ſeverall tongues is no way availeable to Philoſophie, and if a man could ſpeake all manner of Languages, he would be never the more rationall for that, nor more fitting to learn Sciences, then he that hath no more but his owne mother tongue.</p>
            <p>It were much to be wiſhed for the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of men, the concord of Nations, &amp; the communicating of thoughts, that there were but one language in the world; then were it eaſie to travail into farr countries, there would be great facility in commerce, and the whole world would be as it were but one ſtate. But ſince ſo much happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is not to be hoped for, we are at leaſt bound to refine our owne language, and make it uniforme throughout our whole Kingdome; Which if we doe, and fit it ſo, that we may teach Sciences in it, it will grow in as great repute as other Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were, and forraigne Nations will come to us, as they formerly did into <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Aegypt</hi> to learne Sciences.</p>
            <p>It may be objected that the Latine hath a kinde of prerogative above other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, which it holdeth by a publick and univerſall right, that former ages did with ſuch a religious reverence, worſhip and obſerve the uſe of it, and ſome moderne
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152885:34"/>writers, as <hi>Mirandula, Eraſmus, Fernelius, Cardanus, Scaliger, Ramus, Alciat, Cuiacius, Molineus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Craſſot,</hi> have left us many accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates writing therin, of all which we ſhould loſe the benefit, and reading, if we had no other language but <hi>French.</hi> But if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider on the other ſide, that by meanes of tranſlation we may appropiate unto our ſelves any Authours workes, and that as ſoone as we have refined and poliſhed our native tongue, we may tranſlate any either ancient or moderne; this objection will be of no great weight.</p>
            <p>There may againe be objected, that the ſtructure of the Greeke &amp; Latine tongues is more regular, and they may furniſh us with larger meanes of expreſſing our thoughts. But though it be farre from us to lay any imputation or blame upon thoſe noble Languages, yet we may lawfully ſay, that their excellencie conſiſts but in artificiall beauties, and that their orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are more neceſſary for Poets and Orators, then for Philoſophers, who will have the perfection of Languages to conſiſt in having proper names for all known things; with which expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons our tongue is very well furniſhed, and if it be wanting in any thing, it hath been our Anceſtors fault, who have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned their mother tongue; which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152885:34"/>we muſt now amend by our owne care. And why are <hi>Plato, Ariſtotle, Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch, Tullie,</hi> and <hi>Senecaes</hi> workes in ſuch great eſteeme, and credit? it is not for their elegancie, which is but an Axceſſorie, but becauſe they have beene good Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, and have had perfect knowledge of vertue and Sciences. It is therefore, that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braries are filled with their workes, &amp; all ſolid ſpirits deſire to reade them; &amp; not for their Eloquence, &amp; Rethoricall fluency.</p>
            <p>Languages indeed have divers kindes of perfections, ſome excell in abundancie of words to expreſſe their thoughts. And thoſe Nations which have the greateſt knowledge of Divine and Naturall things, and of Arts and Sciences, have alſo a more rich and abounding Language. And therein the firſt and impoſed Language was moſt excellent, it having a proper name for every mine ral, or mixt, that was in the world. Some againe excell in the framing of parts of ſpeeche, when the Nownes, and Verbs are well compoſed, and the Tenſes and Caſes have their juſt terminations, which make the beauty and variety of phraſes, and is a moſt rare ornament to a Language, and therein the Greek &amp; Latine are much to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And ſome againe excell in ſweetneſſe of words, pleaſantneſſe &amp; facility of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:152885:35"/>
            <p>For the number of termes, it is true that there are ſome wanting in the French, for want of refining and poliſhing of it, and becauſe in ſtead of inventing names in our owne mother tongue, for ſuch things as we are newly come to the knowledge of, we have improperly taken them out of the Greeke and Latine, whereby they are not popular, nor intelligible. But if Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences were once brought in and taught amongſt us in our owne mother tongue, that defect would ſoon be ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and amended; ſeeing our Alphabet well known and regulated, is queſtionleſſe more large, and enriched with nine or ten letters, and fifteene or ſixteen diphthonges more then the Greeke, Latine, Italian, or many more, as we ſhall make it largely appeare in our Grammer; wherein we will propoſe the meanes of ſhortning our French Orthographie, and make it wholie conformable to the pronunciation which will make the reading thereof much more eaſie, as well for ſtrangers as our owne Countrimen.</p>
            <p>As for the ſtructure and frame of it, we muſt confeſſe that it hath this defect com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with other Languages, which decline their Nounes by Articles, and conjugate their Verbes with the help and aſsiſtance of the Subſtantive and Auxiliarie Verbe,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152885:35"/>namely to ſpeak in meeter often, and want variety of terminations: and this is the point wherein we muſt chiefly labour in the reformation of our language, it being impoſsible for it otherwiſe to be perfect, &amp; in all points compleate: which thoſe great Poets who lived in <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, and <hi>Henry</hi> the thirds time held to be abſolutely neceſſary. And though it be not ſo curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly regulated, yet it doth not ſo much diſquiet and trouble the mind by the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of words, as artificiall languages doe but contrariwiſe in imitation of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ones, it expreſſeth things in the ſame orders as they come into the minde, and is more proper &amp; eaſie for Philoſophie; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath it ſo many Heteroclites, &amp; irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar words, as the Greeke and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atine have.</p>
            <p>As for the ſweetneſſe and facility of it, ſtrangers themſelves will confeſſe, and certaine it is, that it goeth beyond any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther language therein: and that for two reaſons. The firſt is becauſe it makes an excellent conjunction of betters, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of words, terminating them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatively in Vowels, Conſonants, and ſometimes Diphthonges whereas the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian words end for the moſt part in Vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls, as the Dutch doe in Conſonants; which makes a kinde of unpleaſing ſound through a too frequent rei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eration. The
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152885:36"/>ſecond reaſon is, becauſe the Tones there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are more uniforme, and doe not fall and riſe exceſsively, as they doe in ſome other Languages, men ſeeming to ſing when they ſpeake them, and having ſuch different accents, that it forceth one to writh his mouth and face in pronouncing them. There are alſo proud and boaſting langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as the Spaniſh, which boaſts it ſelfe to be the Language of the Gods; Soft and effeminate, as the <hi>Italian,</hi> which is termed to be womens language; Rough and fierce, as the Northerne, therefore by ſome ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the language of Devills. But the <hi>French</hi> hath none of theſe faults, it is more upright and uniform in its pronunciation, &amp; therefore is called the language of men, as being moſt proper for diſcourſe, being calme and without agitation.</p>
            <p>And yet further to take notice of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and worth of our Language, we may note that there are divers ſorts of ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terances in the world. Some Nations ſeeme to draw their ſpeech out of the very bottom of their breaſts and throates, as the <hi>Hebrew, Dutch</hi> and <hi>Tuſcan, Italian:</hi> Others out of the palate, and the noſe, as the <hi>Italian,</hi> and <hi>Spaniard.</hi> Others ſpeake betweene the teeth, as the <hi>Engliſh, Iriſh, Danes</hi> and others. The <hi>French</hi> only ſpeak through the lipps, as the moſt proper organ,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152885:36"/>and inſtrument: Which is the cauſe they ſpeake quicker, and expreſſe their thoughts more diligently: and this great volubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie proceeds from the facultie of apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the tongue to the lipps, and joyning it with a pleaſing kind of harmonie, and ſo the words follow the thoughts and Imaginations ſo cloſe, that ſtrangers take occaſion thereupon to accuſe the <hi>French</hi> of lightneſſe; whereas it is a great advantage, and as it were a peculiar gift of our nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a property of our climat, which makes our entertainement more pleaſing, our mind more ready at hand, and our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe more cleare. And if our ſpeech ſeem harſh to ſome ſtrangers, it is by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the writing, which is not agreeable to the pronunciation. But the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that is daily endeavored by regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Alphabet, and by giving unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very letter its true and particular character. But it may be ſaid unto me, what art thou, that after ſo many ages, wouldeſt reſtore the <hi>Aegyptian, Greeke,</hi> and <hi>Arabian</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, which hath been ſo long baniſhed out of the world, or rather buried in the tombe of oblivion? who giveth thee now leave to controule a cuſtome approved of by the common conſent of all Nations, for ſo many ages? thinkeſt thou to be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quick-ſighted, and that all thoſe learned
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152885:37"/>men, who were enlightened by the light of Sciences, were ſtricken with a ſpirit of blindneſſe, and did not know which way to teach them? Couldeſt thou not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Sciences being immutable, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a language no way ſubject to changes, and that nationall tongues which change almoſt every age are not ſo proportinable to their ſoliditie as thoſe ancient Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which being no more popular, are not ſubject to any alteration? If thou haſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thus long, and never did'ſt reflect nor looke upon the inconſtancy of popular and nationall languages, behold I will ſhew thee ſome authenticall, and evident proofs thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aegypt</hi> in the time of its Kings, which were called <hi>Pharaohs,</hi> had a certain peculiar &amp; particular language, as may appeare by ſome manuſcripts extant even in our days, which are no way to be underſtood: now the <hi>Arabick</hi> hath ſucceeded in its place, yet we have not retained one word of that ancient Idiome which is reported to have been very large and copious, and more proper then the Greek itſelfe, to treate both of divine and humane Sciences. In <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in former times they ſpake <hi>Syriack,</hi> and now the <hi>Arabick</hi> is there nationall. <hi>Greece</hi> ſo renowned for her Language, is now conſtrained to ſpeake
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152885:37"/>
               <hi>Turkiſh.</hi> The coaſt of <hi>Barbarie,</hi> which in former times ſpake the <hi>Phaenician</hi> tongue, ſpeakes now the <hi>Moors</hi> language. <hi>Gaule</hi> which had a dominion vaſt and powerfull enough to maintaine it ſelfe againſt its enemies, being thorow its owne diviſions at laſt conquered by the <hi>Romans,</hi> hath changed its language three or foure times, in leſſe then ſixteene or ſeventeene hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, and that which we have at this day, is compoſed of the <hi>Celtick, Roman, Franconian</hi> and <hi>Gothick</hi> tongues, and is quite different from the ancient; which <hi>Plinie</hi> who was a <hi>Gaule</hi> borne, and ſpake the Language moſt perfectly, did extoll to the skies. Finally, the <hi>Polonians, Vandalls, Bulgarians, Croatians, Dalmatians, Ruſsians, Bohemians, Lituanians, Moſcovites,</hi> and <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onians,</hi> who in former times knew no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the <hi>Teutonick</hi> or <hi>German</hi> tongue, now together with divers other Nations, ſpeake nothing but the <hi>Sclavonian.</hi> And the <hi>Germans</hi> confeſſe that the Language which themſelves now ſpeake, is quite different from that which they ſpake for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly. We might eaſily name divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations; and were it poſſible to have a regiſter of all the Languages, we ſhould therein finde how they art ſubject to a perpetuall revolution; and that thoſe words which compoſe them, dying in one
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152885:38"/>countrie, and reviving in another, differ in nothing but in the exchange of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and that there are not in nature ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations and corruptions more worthy of admiration, and leſſe admired.</p>
            <p>To anſwer all theſe objections diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they ſeeming to be ſomewhat hard to reſolve, I will firſt ſay, that there can be no valuable inſtance made againſt the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Triſmegiſtus, Ariſtotle, Tullie, Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen,</hi> and the generall cuſtome of thoſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men of former times, who had more underſtanding then we, who never made uſe but onely of nationall languages, in which, though they be ſubject to change, the truth of morall and nationall things remaines perpetually. Of what colour ſoever they painted <hi>Diana</hi> which was in <hi>Chio,</hi> made of white marble, the next day they would find her againe in her naturall whiteneſſe, which painting could not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, nor art corrupt. And if this preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeemes an inviolable law to theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors of Languages, and a ground ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make us forſake the method which was read in ancient times; I would faine know of them whether any preſcription can run againſt the love which we are bound to beare to truth, our countrie, and our mother tongue? and we might alſo conclude from thence, that old errors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152885:38"/>they have been allowed of for a long time, are no errors, which in underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mens judgement are notwithſtanding the moſt pernicious. Cuſtome then can not be a ſufficient defence againſt theſe great and learned men: neither muſt the proceedings of theſe laſt ages, prevaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Method uſed in antient times. They are but Waves beating againſt Rocks; truth will alwaies prevaile: and though wee be growne old and inveterate in errors and diſorders, yet are we not to be excuſed therefore, if we perſiſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Let us rather confeſſe wee have fooliſhly gone aſtray, and acknowledge that the onely meanes to bring us againe into the right way of wiſdom, is, to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate thoſe who in Ancient times preferred Popular, and Nationall Languages before any obſolet and ſtrange tongues.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we do not deny but Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and Mother tongues are ſubject to mixture and corruption: many learned men have obſerved it, and there are too many examples to prove it. But we deny that an obſolet Language can better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Doctrine and Learning of our forefathers then a National. For the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages doe not cauſe Sciences to live, they are but the ſhadowes and figures thereof; but it is the Science which makes the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152885:39"/>to live; and though it have equall dominion over them all ſhe hath it farre more abſolute over the Nation, then over them which are out of date. For proofe whereof, if our Anceſtors, who have written ſo many treaties concerning the firmneſſe of Sciences, and inconſtancie of Languages, had thought it fitting to ſtudy in obſolet Languages, they might have done it as well as wee, ſeeing the <hi>Egyptian</hi> tongue was in the time of the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> and the Greek under the <hi>Arabians</hi> was not mentioned, nor found but onely in Books. But theſe great men knew too well that they could not bring in ſo pernicious, and ridiculous a cuſtome, without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſing Sciences with thouſands of difficulties, and fruſtrating many men, who could not learn ſtrange Languages, of the hope of attaining to the Knowledge of them Wherefore rejecting all other Languages, as unprofitable waies, and extravagant meanes, they moſt judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly brought th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir youth directly to the Knowledge of Sciences by the abbrevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate way of their mother tongue.</p>
            <p>But fully to ſatisfie the objection of thoſe who ſay, that popular and naturall Languages are too variable to deſerve the honor of being interpreters of Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and expoſiters of mens beſt thoughts;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152885:39"/>We affirm that they are more conſtant, and leſſe ſubject to change then the obſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let. For though they ſeem be to exempted and free from alteration, and incapable of increaſe or diminution, becauſe they are not ſubject to the mutable will of men, but are continually taught by the ſame rules; yet ought we not to attribute unto them a perpetuall laſtingneſſe; ſeeing that the power of a Conqueror, that hates learning, may on a ſuddain annihilate thoſe languages, as the <hi>Turk</hi> hath done in all his Dominions. And all things rightly conſidered, no Monarch can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt thoſe remainders of antient Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages which wee have from the juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of time, nor protect them againſt ſome inevitable chances, the leaſt of which may abſolutely deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>The firſt Language which had ſo many prerogatives above others, gives us a faire example of this truch; the firſt inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the World had imprinted it, not upon paper, as we do now, but upon moſt ſolid and hard columnes, that they might make it live for ever, and tranſmit the memory thereof to poſterity: Yet for all that, it vaniſhed away by little and little, and that faire monument hath been ſo little regarded, that there remaines not
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152885:40"/>now any ſigne thereof. We may likewiſe alleage to this purpoſe, that the Jewiſh Language was wholly extinguiſhed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Captivity. It was the Organ whereby the will of God was ſet downe, and the antient Law was written in it: <hi>Eſdras,</hi> and the Doctors had preſerved the underſtanding of it: yet at laſt they let it periſh, judging it more convenient to tranſlate the ſacred Hiſtory in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue, then to bind the people to the re-eſtabliſhment, and the learned to the preſervation of a Language newly loſt. Finally the <hi>Roman</hi> Annals make faith that the antient <hi>Roman</hi> Language, of which the Prieſts onely had preſerved the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, hath been ſubject to the like over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw: the Libraries were full of it, the Sibylles verſes, the Hymnes and Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were written in it, the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate had profeſſed and declared it ſelf to be the preſerver of it, and yet all this could not keep it from a totall ruine.</p>
            <p>Moreover, although the nationall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages be ſubject to the innovation of ſome words; yet experience ſheweth us, that thoſe which have had any extent, or merit, either by being poliſhed by poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Nations, who knew how to bring them to perfection, at home by the means of Sciences, and abroad by way of armes
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152885:40"/>in defending themſelves, have not been ſo ſubject to periſh; and will outlaſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages before they be quite aboliſhed. Witneſs the Greek, which remained en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire for above two thouſand yeares, and would have laſted longer, if the Turkiſh domination had not cut off the courſe of ſo many years, which it might yet have lived. It is certain that the Romans ſtrove with all their might to aboliſh the language of the Gaules, whom they had ſubdued; yet their deſign could not fully come to paſs, and we have to this day ſome of it in this Kingdom, which hath no communion nor part with the Latin, which evidently ſhewes that it was never there: nor the vulgar and mother tongue never ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>Whereby we may inferre that popular Languages, which are ſo hardly ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, may be continued farre better and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilier then thoſe forgotten ones which can not be preſerved without much difficultie; and that they are more proper to ſerve for inſtruments to Sciences. Nationall Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages likewiſe decay by degrees, and are aboliſhed by ſucceſſion oftimes. But thoſe obſolete ones, which have no more being but onely in Libraries, and ſubſiſt onely by art, may periſh and comeſiſt nought in an inſtant. And if the Romans,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152885:41"/>who were ſo carefull in univerſaliſing their language, had found none to oppoſe them but onely Obſolet tongues, and books; they would have aboliſhed the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of them in an inſtant, and would not have found ſo much oppoſition in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Latin tongue into all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces which were ſubject to their Empire.</p>
            <p>Moreover have we not great cauſe to to doubt, whether the Latin tongue which hath been extinguiſhed theſe ſix or ſeven hundred years, and hath laſted to our times onely by the meanes of Colledges and univerſities, will laſt ſo long as the Greek, the Gaule, and many other. Thoſe who come in after ages, will know the Succeſs thereof better than wee. As for the preſent, to come to underſtand why popular, and nationall Languages are more laſting, and fitting to teach Sciences in then the obſolet, we ought to obſerve that in every Language there are two ſorts of words. Some are familiar and vulgar, which ſerve for common diſcourſe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proper, pecul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar and effectuall onely for Tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and arts. The firſt depend upon the people, which hath power to alter the names of ſuch things as it hath uſe of to entertain ſociety, the latter are within the Philoſophers jurisdiction, who have power to give names to all things, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152885:41"/>to Arts and Sciences. The firſt are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to change, and do not laſt alwaies; partly becauſe they ſignifie nothing but ſingular, contingent, and caſuall objects; partly becauſe they are ſubject to the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of a light, and inconſtant multitude: but that alteration that is, ſo ſmall, that there wilſcarce be a hundred of thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon words altered in a hundred years. It is not ſo in thoſe words which belong to Arts and trades, it is in a manner impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to alter them; and after they are once in uſe, the common people have no power over them, they are kept in by a myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous way, they are of ſo good a temper, and ſuch ſolid matter, that they ſtand firm and immoveable, whileſt other names are toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and turned upſide down, by the gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-headed Rabble.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why they are ſo firme and conſtant is becauſe they are applied to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie firme and conſtant things, ſuch as the mater als &amp; inſtruments of Arts are; it is not caſte to change them and put others in ſtead of them. And if artiſts, who are the diſpoſers of them, and to communicate &amp; teach them to their apprentices with the ſame fidelity as they received them of their maſter, ſhould aſſume ſo much li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to themſelves as to innovate and alterthem, and bring in new according
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152885:42"/>to their own fancies, naming one and the ſame thing which belongs to their trade, in one countrie by one name, and in another otherwiſe, they would not within a ſhort time underſtand one another, nor maintain that correſpondency and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood which is amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Therefore they are much miſ-informed concerning the nature of things, who would have Sciences taught in obſolet and forgotten Languages, to give them as it were innumerable termes. They doe not conſider that the terms of Arts and Sciences may eaſily be perpetuated in all Languages, ſo they be poliſhed and refin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Wherefore we are both of one opinion in this; that we ought to teach Sciences in firm and durable tongues, but we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that Nationall Languages are more durable then the obſolet ones; and that for diverſe reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe the termes of Arts and Sciences are no ſooner invented, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of in a ſpeech, but they of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves doe preſerve themſelves therein, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as the termes of a trade without any trouble or labour: and if there ſhould be any paines required therein, they might without compariſon befarre more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filier learned &amp; preſerved in a Nationall &amp; popular Language, then in an obſolet one.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:152885:42"/>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon is, becauſe ſuppoſe the Language of the Country were ſubject to ſome change, one may hinder them from changing with it, by forbidding any new ones to be brought in, and ſo they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining as they were, may be ſtill apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the various changes of other popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar words. By which meanes all ſcholaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call termes have remained in their firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for theſe five or ſix laſt ages, though the reſt of the Latin tongue have varied much ſince that time, as we may ſee by thoſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors that have written in thoſe ages.</p>
            <p>The third is, that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anguages being preſerved by the induſtry of men, it will be farre eaſier to keep a ſmall portion of a National language from periſhing, then to revive a whol language which is quite out of date and forgotten. For youth may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily and in a ſmall time be inſtructed in the termes of that profeſſion, which it meanes to follow; they being but few in number, and not the hundreth part of the words of a full and compleat Language: ſo that they may be learned with ſmall paines, and as it were inſenſibly, before one think of it; And learning their own Countrie Language naturally, they ſhall be exempted from the tediouſneſs and difficulty of learning the Latin tongue, wherein they ſpend ten or twelve yeares
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152885:43"/>of their beſt time, to make them capable of underſtanding three or four hundred barbarous words, which have been fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Univerſities within ſix or ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hundred yeares, by ignerant perſons who never knew the Latin tongue in its purity. Yet they have been ſo induſtrious and fortunate in their proceedings, that they have brought theſe words into ſo much credit and eſtimation, that it hath been commonly thought they could not be expreſſed in any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anguage, and that they had a particular energie and vertue to ſignifie thoſe things. But, in truth there is no ſuch matter; for if you come to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine them necrly, you will find they ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie nothing at all, they are not polite, and cannot be tranſlated, nor yet underſtood in any language, if the phraſe and Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxis of them be not mended; it being moſt certain that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atin Philoſophers ſpeech is not leſs ridiculous and barbarous in their own Language, then it is in ours. And if any eſteem them politer and more ſignificant then ours, it is becauſe they have been ſo long accuſtomed to them, that they cannot eaſily find the defaults and diſorderlineſs of them.</p>
            <p>But ſuch as are well verſed in the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of Languages, know, that the verſion of a perfect diſcourſe, hath a great deal of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152885:43"/>grace, and Elegancy in all Countries; and contrariwiſe a thing il penned in one Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, is nonſence, and abſurd in all other. Whereby wee may inferre, that the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in tranſlating of theſe termes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes not from any particular merit in them, or from the imperfection of other Languages, but from their owne defect and evill conſtruction. For proof and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all whereof, if you tranſlate them into the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Arabick,</hi> which admit of none, but proper and uſuall termes in their Philoſophy; you ſhall find preſently that your tranſlation will be no more intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, or better compoſed, then if it had been in <hi>Spaniſh, Italian,</hi> or any other vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Nationall Language. And this is the reaſon why thoſe who have ſtudyed Philoſophy in Latin, underſtand it not in their own Language, and dare not ſpeak of it before men of their own Nation, for fear of making themſelves ridiculous; whereas thoſe who have learned it in an Elegant and refined Nationall Language of their own, can eaſily expreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in any other Language which they can underſtand and ſpeak.</p>
            <p>This is the chief argument which the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors of theſe obſolet Lauguages make uſe of againſt us, and which they igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly borrow from the laſtingneſſe of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152885:44"/>them, never regarding the facility and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, which is the onely abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary condition required for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of a Language which is made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall for the attaining of Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. And as the mother tongue is moſt caſie; ſo queſtionleſſe it is the beſt fitted and proportioned to mens ſpirits, and moſt conformable to the intentions of nature, which deſtining us to ſome end, furniſheth us with moſt eaſie and pleaſing meanes to attain thereunto, according as it ſelfe is moſt Noble, and excellent. I would wilingly ask our Antagoniſts, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would not hold it a moſt ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous thing in Artiſts, if they ſhould introduce a cuſtome amongſt themſelves to ſpeak of their Art only in a ſtrange and unknown Language, putting their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices to the task of beſtowing ten or twelve yeares ſtudy in learning of a hard and troubleſome tongue, onely to make them capable of Underſtanding one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or two ſtrange termes of their calling and Vocation.</p>
            <p>And if they anſwer, that the termes of Sciences, Arts, and Trades, will take up halfe the words of a Language, and that therefore they are not ſo eaſie to be learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. We reply again, that no man ought, or need, to learne them all, but that every
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152885:44"/>one is onely bound to poſſeſſe himſelfe of thoſe which neceſſarily belong to his own profeſſion. And again, ſuppoſe that even theſe termes ſhould alter and be ſubject to changes as well as the reſt of a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, yet that argues not that we ſhould teach Sciences in any other but the Mother Tongue. Seeing tranſlation may eaſily, and faithfully make an antient Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage Moderne: And that it is beyond compariſon more eaſie, to tranſlate our forefathers Language into our own, then in thoſe forlorne and forraign ones.</p>
            <p>As for the tranſlation of forraign Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, all learned Nations, <hi>Jewes, Greeks, Romans,</hi> and <hi>Arabians,</hi> have uſed it. And though it be ſomewhat hard to turne ſo many Antient workes into our mother tongue, yet we may truly ſay, that it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in compariſon of the trouble and care which ſo many thouſands of brave ſpirits have undergone in the tedious compaſſing of thoſe forgotten Languages. And wee have already naturalized, and taught to ſpeak French, the moſt excellent and rareſt Authors that writ in former ages, ſo that if we continue labouring in tranſlations with the ſame fervencie as we have be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un ſince the French Academy was erected; within theſe thirty years wee
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152885:45"/>ſhall not have any thing left to tranſlate, but ſhall in our owne Mother tongue poſſeſs the Riches of all other Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            <p>Finally it would not be very difficult to invent a more generall, more conſtant, and more eaſie inſtrument, then that of forlorn tongues, which ſhould repreſent things by Characters, which youth might learn with a great deal more eaſe then the words of an aboliſhed Language, neither would they any way hinder the Mother tongue: and thoſe who had learned thoſe Characters, ſeeing ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain markes, would withall conceive the minds of others, and might preſently by other Characters diſcloſe their own. So that thoſe who ſhould be well verſed in this ſecret, would underſtand one another without being underſtood; and without ſpeaking, would converſe with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, every one in his own Language; which would queſtionleſſe be a moſt pleaſant kind of recreation. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, if a Frenchman writes in the preſence of an <hi>Italian,</hi> or a <hi>German,</hi> 1640 the other preſently reads and underſtands, and can expreſſe in his own Language what thoſe Characters ſignifie. This would indeed be a rare art, and ſo much the more to be admired, becauſe it would in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152885:45"/>repreſent the ſame thing, neither would the Characters change, though the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages did. There might alſo uſe be made of theſe Characters onely, for the termes of Arts and Sciences, to the end the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry might not be overburthened with the exceſſive number, and in all other things make uſe of the Nationall ſpeech. But neither is this invention as proper as the mother tongue, and though it have been formerly uſed by learned men, yet is it not worth the reviving, becauſe it would be accompanied with many difficulties, which ought as much as may be to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided for the good and eaſe of learners. I queſtion not but that Sciences are very at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive, &amp; every one naturally deſires to attain them; but yet they wil be ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but by very few, if the way vnto them be not made eaſie and pleaſant. We are inventing every day new Methods, to ſhorten and levell the way which guides us thereunto, and yet it is every day more and more encumbred, and difficulties in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe continually. We ſhall never have any famous men ſpring up amongſt us, what art ſoever wee uſe, unleſſe wee teach in our owne Nationall Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.</p>
            <p>Finally it is certaine, that Sciences can not be preſerved by any immutable thing,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152885:46"/>but onely by the Species, which alwaies poſſeſſing the Underſtanding in the ſame manner, oblige it to conceive all things in the ſame faſhion. Nature uſes no other Language to ſpeak to all men, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in the Knowledge of the truth. Thence it comes that they apprehend an Elephant, an Eagle, a Dolphin, all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner, and they every where produce the ſame imaginations and Phantaſmaes; in the uſe, and perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion whereof conſiſts all manner of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. The Species, and the word, have this common to them, that they both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the truth, but this is the difference between them, that the Species being a naturall, and immutable ſigne, muſt of neceſſity be the ſame in all places: and the word being an arbitrary and tranſitorie mark, muſt be different every where; ſo that we may truly ſay, that the ſpecies or notion which repreſents all things to the mind of man, is the onely Language which did never change, and will alwaies be common to all men; becauſe the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which preſent them to our ſences, are not changeable, and make themſelves to be knowne every where after the ſame manner: whereas Characters, Geſtures, and words depending meerly upon our will, are every where different. Wee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152885:46"/>the objects, not beauſe they are <hi>Greek, Latin, Dutch, &amp;c.</hi> but becauſe they have a relation to our notion, and ſignifie that which is in our minds. Which is the reaſon that though the Languages of Nations be various, yet they cauſe no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie in the notions of the mind: That which the <hi>French</hi> calls <hi>Pierre,</hi> the <hi>German Steen,</hi> the <hi>Latin Lapis,</hi> the <hi>Greeke</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the <hi>Engliſh Stone,</hi> is but one meer notion, although theſe names be different; ſeeing they repreſent but one and the ſelf ſame thing to the underſtandings of all theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>Therefore all things well conſidered, there is no readier way can be made to Sciences, then by the naturall and mother tongue; and if ours finds it ſelf wanting of ſome traines to explaine the ſubtilities of Sciences, we may eaſily ſupply that want by inventing names therefore by the help of the Profeſſors of the <hi>French</hi> Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy, and other learned men; to the end that they may paſs through their appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, and that nothing may be inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated without good advice. And our <hi>French</hi> tongue hath herein this advantage, that in reference to Sciences, it is not yet engaged in any evil or barbarous termes, introduced by any long cuſtome, which it would be more difficult to aboliſh, then
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152885:47"/>to invent new. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelfe, though he diſallowed of many <hi>Greek</hi> termes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Philoſophy, durſt not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to reform them, fearing to ſeeem an Innovator of antiquity, and to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe odious to thoſe of his owne times: So that Philoſophy hath alwaies beene mixed with improper and ambiguous termes. But wee having now free liberty, and learned men good ſtore amongſt us, may very well Naturalize Sciences in our own Country, inventing proper termes for them, and laying aſide all ſuch as might make Philoſophy ambiguous, barbarous, and unpleaſant.</p>
            <p>And to this end we ſhall cut off all Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyonymies and Equivocalls which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the mind, and intangle and trouble Arts and Sciences. For Philoſophy will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ever be plain, ſo long as one thought may have diverſe names, and whilſt wee ſtrive to ſpeak Equivocally in Philoſophy: it were much more to the purpoſe, to finde out ſome one that would ſtrike out al thoſe Equivocall words out of the Grammer.</p>
            <p>When an opinion is introduced, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized and rooted through preſcription of time, it hath a marvellous power over our minds: which makes us ſo preoccupated and prepoſſeſſed with the excellency of antient Languages; Thoſe who have not
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152885:47"/>attained to them, admire them becauſe they doe not underſtand them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is ſo much difficulty in the learning of them: and thoſe who have Knowledge in them, being intereſted in the preſervation of them, ſet forth their praiſes, but will by no means diſcover the defects of them; and wilfully maintaine that they are more effectuall, and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant then the moderne, the very Gates that open the way to Sciences, and the onely means to attaine them; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding if we may ſpeak the truth freely, we may eaſily make it appear, that they are all of equall value, and have no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative one above the other.</p>
            <p>For all words that can be imagined are of like nature, having the ſame finall, and the ſame efficient cauſe, the ſame matter, and the ſame forme. They have the ſame finall cauſe, namely to expreſſe our thoughts; The ſame, efficient cauſe, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the power of the man which produceth them: The ſame, matter, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Letters and Dipthonges: And finally they have the ſame forme, being made different onely in termination, and the laſt letter, which is as it were the ſeale and character, which hath the power of making up their eſſence, as the laſt unit makes up that of numbers. All the vertue
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152885:48"/>&amp; energie, they have from the authoritie of men, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> can give no advantage to the one more then to the other; For it is but a meer <hi>Being of Reaſon,</hi> proceeding out of an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute hazard and occurrencie. For indeed there is, nor can be but one way of ſpeaking in the whole world, the difference is but onely in characters, and geſtures, and we attribute to ſeverall impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the name of difference of Languages.</p>
            <p>Languages proceed not from without, as ſome are of opinion, who imagine that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were divinely inſpired, or came to us by tradition: but we have the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall or root of them in ourſelves; and if we be ignorant of the cauſes of he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of them, it is becauſe they are too common, and are every day ſubject to our ſenſes. Common and continuall cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome deceaves us, and are the cauſe that we perceive not the mouth to be the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Matrix and Alphabet, and as it were a large caſe out of which all words doe iſſue, and into which are put, and as it were diſtributed by the Author of Nature, all the ſeverall letters, as into a little box, from whence every man like to a Printer takes them out when he pleaſes, compoſes them and maketh up languages. And God having endowed him with manifold perfections above all other creatures, hath
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152885:48"/>given him nothing which is more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to him then ſpeech, ſeeing thereby he is made capable of knowing and loving him his maker, lives in Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and attaines Wiſdom: Wherefore he would have thoſe parts wherein the voice of man is framed, filled up with ſo many wonders, to make us the better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the worth of them, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bind us to an acknowledgement of ſo rare a benefit.</p>
            <p>But it is not ſufficient to know that theſe parts do with ſuch celeritie mixe the letters, and frame words out of them, which we make uſe of in familiar com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication; but we muſt alſo note that each part hath its particular functions, and proper motions, yet differing amongſt themſelves: and every man pronouncing a letter, may know and marke the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan which frameth it, and gives it its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and what part concurres moſt to the production of it, whether it be the lips, the palate, or the tongue, that hath moſt operation in it. And that which is moſt of all to be admited is, that all theſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans are ſo well regulated, and obſerve ſo r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> an order amongſt themſelves, that they can not incroach nor uſurp upon the rights of one another, their power being ſo well limitted, that they can juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152885:49"/>to frame ſo many letters and no more, then a man can make ſeverall and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent motions and doublings in his mouth. Which ſhewes ſufficiently all Languages to be of equall worth, and that if there be any difference betweene them, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not from the words, which are all of the ſame matter in all Languages, but rather from the Pronunciation, which depending upon the Climates, is more milde and pleaſant in thoſe Countries, where the peoples Organs are moſt clear and beſt compoſed; and contrariwiſe is more harſh and diſſonant in thoſe where they are more groſſely and rudely framed. And this talent is the more conſiderable, being as it were deſtin'd to ſome Nations, and doth not vary though the ranguages alter, and change by ſucceſſion of time. The faculty wee have of framing words <hi>in infinitum</hi> is the richeſt treaſure belongs to man, it is a continually flowing and running fountaine, which can never be dried up. Wherefore it is a folly to complain of the barrenneſſe of a I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, it is our faults if wee do not enrich it, if wee will but apply our endeavours to it. And an ingen ous Arithmetician in coupling of letters and joyning of ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, might give an admirable ſtructure to all the parts of ſpeech, and frame a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,
<pb facs="tcp:152885:49"/>and more regular Language then yet there is. For the combination of letters is a well that can never be drawn dry, out of which one may frame, as out of <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria prima,</hi> words enough, for an infinite number of Languages, all different a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves; ſo that in ſo greate a number of ſpeeches as are ſpoken in the whole World, men do not hit upon the impoſition of the ſame names.</p>
            <p>Whence it appeares that the diverſity of Languages proceedes from the plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of words, and the liberty of Framing them; and not from the difference of Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates. Becauſe we being all indifferent, and having no more aptitude the one then the other to expreſſe the ſignification of things, the will would alwaies remaine in ſuſpence, and would never reſolve up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Election; if the inclination which it hath to declare its thoughts, did not oblige it to take names by chance, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them at adventure. Which thing would evidently appear, if a company of little Children were kept up in ſeverall houſes in one Plaine, who would queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe make as many ſeverall Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as ſeverall companies which were ſhut together. For as concerning that which is ſpoken of an infant, which was bred up in ſolitude, and apart, and could pronounce
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152885:50"/>but this word <hi>Bec,</hi> it was a moſt groſſe ignorance in thoſe who imagined to have a certain proofe and evident teſtimony thereby, of which was the moſt ancient and naturall Language; ſeeing the child was brought up ſolitary and alone, in which caſe fooles and madmen onely will lye talking and diſcourſing with themſelves: Outward ſpeech being a thing neceſſary onely to impart our thoughts to others, and not to ſpeak to our ſelves, who underſtand our own thoughts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out expreſſing them outwardly. They ſhould therefore to finde out the effect of ſo rare a curioſitie, have put a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of children, rather then one, or two, together. Whereupon wee muſt obſerve, that if Nature ſeem to have done man great prejudice, and much hindred the communication of Nations, by giving them abſolute power to make ſo many Languages: She hath alſo given him power and meanes to obviate that incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, making him politick, where by he might find, that to make up moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Societies and Common-wealths happy, he ſhould carefully ſuppreſſe all particular Languages, to bring in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and common ſpeeches amongſt all Nations.</p>
            <p>Now this great variety proceeds from
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152885:50"/>two Originall cauſes, Namely the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency and infiniteneſſe of words; They are indifferent, becauſe Naturally they ſignifie nothing, and are equally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſignifie any thing. They are almoſt infinite, becauſe there reſults an infinite number, not onely of words, but alſo of Languages out of the conjunction and copulation of letters and ſyllables; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one alone may ſignifie all things one after another, even as well as one onely thing may receive all manner of names ſucceſſively according as men ſhall be willing to apply them unto it.</p>
            <p>The number of letters which are day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed, is not yet well known, nor regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated. Men ſeeme to have been very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in not ordering a matter of ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance; for if they had well examined the nature of the Alphabet, they might have had it a great deal more full and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious. But howſoever as it is, we have twentie, or two and twentie letters which are now in uſe. And is it not a thing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be admired, to ſee ſo many Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages built upon ſo ſmall a foundation? and by the copulation and tranſpoſition of ſo few letters, ſo great a number of words made, to which men unawares ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtoming themſelves, have framed ſo many particular Languages: From
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152885:51"/>whence wee muſt neceſſarily conclude, that all of them proceeding from one beginning, they are eſſentially equall, and cannot any way differ, but onely in the quantity of termes whereof they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. Wherefore all men have equall Power and Right to give names to ſuch things, as yet have none: eſpecially Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, to whom it belongs to invent names, to repreſent things rightly, and ſet them in a due courſe: they have full power to ſet downe termes for Sciences, and Arts, to make themſelves intell gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and communicate their learning to others.</p>
            <p>Wee may likewiſe in imitation of the <hi>Greekes</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> borrow of our neighbour Languages ſome termes which may be wanting in our own; for although for a time they paſſe for ſtrangers, yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome few years, they are naturalized, and conform themſelves ſo well to the tone of the Nation, that there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to be found in them. The <hi>Romans</hi> did not alwaies ſtrive to tranſlate into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atin all Greek words, as Rhetorick, Muſick, Arithmetick, Geometrie, Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, Philoſophie, Chirurgerie, and moſt of the names of Sciences, and Arts of Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, of Herbes, of Diſeaſes, and many other things: They have been content
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152885:51"/>to adopt them, and admit them into their community; Knowing that all words, both Greek and other, are of common right, and belong to all Nations equally who deſire to make uſe of them; and that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anguages lend &amp; borrow words, to, and from each other continually. For though it be not manifeſtly known that the Greekes borrowed the termes of Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences from other Nations, yet it is credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that they brought them with them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> where they went to ſtudy: and that the <hi>Egyptians</hi> likewiſe borrowed them from ſome other more ancient Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which might invent them when they firſt invented Philoſophie. And if this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendencie be odious, to free our ſelves from it, wee need but alter the Etymolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, imitating learned <hi>Varro</hi> therein, who being aſhamed that ſo many Latin words ſhould deſcend from the Greek, for the honour of his Nation, derived them from other ſeverall Languages of <hi>Italie.</hi> When one doth not indeed underſtand the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of a ſtrange word, he may have recourſe to the Originall; but when it is once come into cuſtome, it is no more needfull, the meaneſt artiſt knowing the ſignification thereof as well as the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Doctor. As for example, the common people do not know that the words Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152885:52"/>Apoplexie, and Propheſie are Greek words; and yet they underſtand as well what they meane, as he that hath ſtudied the Greek Grammer twenty yeares.</p>
            <p>Finally Pilots have found out termes enough for Sea affaires, Architects, for Architecture, and ſo have all other Artiſts for their ſeverall Arts. And is it not a ſhame, that Philoſophers have not in ſo many ages found a way in <hi>France</hi> to invent neceſſarie words for our <hi>French</hi> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie?</p>
            <p>It is certaine that when Gunnes, Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and other new Arts were firſt inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Authors thereof had no proper termes for them, and yet now we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance. And when King <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt commanded all to plead in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue, the people which belonged to the Courts of Juſtice were at firſt aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at it; and ſome did even deſpaire of going forward in their profeſſion: Yet we ſee how in a ſhort time they have found out as many termes as ever the <hi>Greeke</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi> law had; and would to God they had not invented ſo many.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe about a bundred yeares ſince, all Poetrie lay as it were dead in <hi>French,</hi> and eſpecially Comick Poems were ſo
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152885:52"/>barren and dull, that none did ſcarce dare to ſhew themſelves upon the Stage. Yet by little and little they have been ſo adorned and beautified, eſpecially now of late daies they have, thorow your Eminencies beneficence, ſo increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Elegancie and Politeneſſe, that the Theaters Eccho with acclamations and applauſes.</p>
            <p>If our Language were now as barren and imperfect as heretofore it hath beene, I muſt confeſſe our enterpriſe would at firſt be ſomewhat hard and difficult. But it is now enriched, and hath abundancie of words to explaine our thoughts. They now can reade publick Lectures of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie and Mathematicks in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue, and Divines can unfold the deepe myſteries of Divinity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and make them intelligible even to the plaineſt and dulleſt underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p>But againſt all theſe reaſons they will peradventure alleadge, that thoſe who ſtudy Philoſophy in <hi>French,</hi> never came to be abſolute Philoſophers. But that is not through the defect of the Language, or of Philoſophy it ſelf but rather through want of method. Thoſe who learne it in <hi>Latin</hi> privately, profit not a whit more: The reaſon is becauſe that thoſe maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152885:53"/>which teach privately in chambers, endeavour nothing but onely to pleaſe and content their auditors; reading lect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures full of cavills, and oſtentation, no way tending to ſolid inſtruction. This ſchooling is but a kind of paſtime; even as in Comedies, where the Actor ſeeks onely to tickle the itching eares of the hearers to draw on more company, and ſo encreaſe his gaine. A Science requires Method and Diſcipline; it is not enough to be a hearer, he muſt alſo excrciſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in what he heares, and reduce the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts into practiſe, by diſputat ons, repiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and conferences. Thus are the Spirits heated, and chafed, whereby doctrine is the deeplier imprinted in our memories. Sciences are like Arts; to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a good Artiſt, it is not ſufficient to frequent the Shopps of the moſt expert artiſts, unleſſe we ſet our hands to work likewiſe. How many men doe wee ſee daily, who have aſſiduouſly and with good attention heard fâmous prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers for the ſpace of twenty or thirty yeares, and yet are not ſo well verſed in Divinity as a Scholler of the Sorbonne, who hath heard lectures there but a year, by reaſon that the Profeſſors in that reverend Society, are Methodicall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who after their rare expoſitions, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152885:53"/>exerciſe their auditors in diſputation, both in the Schooles privately, and alſo in other publick Acts. And now that his Majeſty hath by his eſtabliſhment as it were naturalized Philoſophy, and made it in a manner popular &amp; methodicall, we muſt hope that within a ſhort time, youth will beſolidely learned, through the care of a regular diſcipline. For it is true both in Schoole and State buſineſs, that it is not ſufficient to propound good Maximes, unleſſe they be well maintained and punctually obſerved, through the rules of a good government.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, as for theſe two laſt meanes (which are of moſt moment) namely to teach the Grammer and Diſcipline, the Profeſſors of the Academy cannot imploy themſelves about it; they have higher matters to look after, and have not leiſure to inſtruct youth. In thoſe works which proceed from them, the rules of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite writing are indeed very punctually obſerved, but thoſe works come not to every ones hands, ſome few ſtudents, and refined court Spirits onely make uſe of them and profit thereby. How many Gentlemen are there in the country, who neuer hear of them and if they ſhould, yet are not capable of ſuch high reflections? They never came out of their fathers hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152885:54"/>but only to practiſe their exerciſes, or to go to the wars, at their return from whence it is too late for them to be inſtructed. They are not well prepared for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſuch books with any profit; which makes them all their life time to uſe the <hi>Britiſh, Norman,</hi> or <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi> Dialect: Which many times keeps them from comming to the Court, retired at their homes in idleneſſe, where they beſtow their times in nothing but hunting and husbandry. Whereas their parents might in time ſend them to the City of <hi>Richelieu,</hi> where for a ſmall charge, and in a little time they might be taught Sciences, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages and Exerciſes altogether, whilſt they are yet young enough, and may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily forget the ill accent of their own country Language, and without Labour accuſtome themſelves to a better Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation, to choice and pureneſs of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. So that returning afterwards into their own countrie, though the Language be there extreamely corrupt, they will ſpeak good <hi>French</hi> all their life time. Their companions and Tenants will follow their example, men alwaies natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally inclining to novelties, eſpecially when they are according to reaſon, and judiciouſly invented.</p>
            <p>So ſhall we make way throughout the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152885:54"/>whole Kingdome for thoſe Maximes which the Profeſſors of the Academy ſhall ſet downe; and your Eminencie ſhall have the glory of being the reſtorer both of your Native Countrie, and Language. The Chancellor of the Hoſpitall, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that deſign, which now your Eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie hath approved of, would be very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and uſefull to this Nation, had an intent to erect certain French Colledges in <hi>Paris,</hi> where Sciences ſhould be taught in our mother Tongue, which he judged to be fitting therefore, even in thoſe daies. This famous man perceiving the abuſe and error of former ages, could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to ſee the <hi>French</hi> Nation, which had founded ſo many brave Schooles, and maintained ſo many profeſſers to teach the <hi>Hebrew, Arabick, Greek</hi> &amp; <hi>Latin</hi> tongus, neglect to build one for their own. Since his time the Cardinall <hi>du Perron,</hi> infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the like zeale did againe attempt that glorious deſigne, and ſought all meanes poſſible to bring it to paſs. And laſt of all <hi>Monſieur de Freſne Canage,</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by his example to animate us to teach Sciences in <hi>French,</hi> writ an Organon in our Language to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, fraught with ſo much learning &amp; elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that we may boldly ſay he hath not only equalled, but even exceeded the moſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152885:55"/>excellenteſt <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Authors. But the compleating of this great work was reſerved for your Eminency to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh; and ſeems to have been deferred hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, onely that you might have the full glory of eſtabliſhing a buſineſs of ſo great importance.</p>
            <p>This Sir will be the firſt fruit which the inſtitution of your Academy in the City of <hi>Richelieu,</hi> will bring forth, namely the regulating and refining the Language in all the Povinces of this Kingdome, which will be very advantagious for the glory of it. And your Eminency will be pleaſed to let me tell you, that there will other ſolid benefits accruew thereby. Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen will no more ſpend their youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full time in unprofitable toyes, they will directly learn ſuch things as are neceſſary to direct &amp; guide them through the whole courſe of their life, the mutuall duties of Society, their Princes ſervice, the love of their Native Country, and their due acknowledgement to your Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie.</p>
            <p>It is a great abuſe to mixe Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with perſons of baſe extraction, and to bring them up after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for beſides that it takes ſordide and baſe inclinations, unworthy its birth, and ſuch imployments as it may
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152885:55"/>one day hope for, it alſo receaveth ſuch inſtructions as are not fitting for it, and overburthens its mind uſeleſsely all the remainder of their lives.</p>
            <p>True it is, that if parents did predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate their children to be Churchmen, Lawyers, Phyſitians, or to live continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally within the precinct of a Library, then it is fitting to have them to know the ſecrets of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> tongue, the Origine and Etymologie of words, and make them famous Criticks; becauſe the Fathers of the Church, the Civill Law, and the Authors of Phyſick are written in thoſe Languages, and are not yet tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into <hi>French.</hi> But in a gentleman that meanes to wear a ſword by his ſide, theſe things are needleſſe; and the knowledge of theſe Languages, would make him ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the fitter for his countries ſervice.</p>
            <p>Why doe Parents neglect to ſend their children to colledges, and let them lye at home till they be of age to learn Exerciſes, in the meane time their youth is ſpent in idleneſſe, their memory and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding growes weak through want of employment, &amp; become as it were lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing faculties? Others will not ſend them to the Academies, as well by reaſon of the exceſſive charge, as alſo becauſe they are not there inſtructed in learning. They
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152885:56"/>learn indeed to ride, dance, and fence, which makes their bodies active, and their joints ſupple: but though theſe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities add ſome grace to the body, yet can they not make a compleat Gentleman; contrariwiſe they make him raſh and bold, if they be not accompanied with perfections of the mind. But if they were taught in the vulgar, and mother tongue, Vertue, the duties of an honeſt man, and all thoſe things which belong both to peace and warr together with their exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, they would profitably employ each moment of their youth, become at once active and learned, and be fit for counſell, execution, and all manner of employment whatſoever.</p>
            <p>This is the order which your Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency obſerves in his houſe, you cauſe your Pages to be equally bred up in arts and Exerciſes, according to their age and capacity; making choice of the beſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and tutors that can be had in every profeſſion. Your houſe being thus orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red is a Seminary of honor and vertue, and there come more compleat gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men out of your ſervice, then out of all the Colledges &amp; Academies of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Theſe are young plants which grow up for your Glory, you engrave your benefits upon the bark of hoſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152885:56"/>plants, and the character which you imprint thereon increaſe with time, to your honor, and the good of the ſtate: and <hi>France</hi> acknowledges, amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other benefits, that you dayly ſtore it with moſt vertuous and compleat Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <p>Your Eminency (who knoweth better then any one, that he education of youth is the ground and foundation both of a publick and private life, upon which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends the happineſſe of families, and the greatneſſe of Empires) erects publick Academies, and payes ſeverall great pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in colledges for children, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving rare naturall parts, want means to give them education, charitably eaſing the Parents poverty, and the Orphans mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, beſtowing means upon them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may become capable of ſerving the State, every one according to his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius and profeſſion. Thus Sr. your Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency doth dayly free the <hi>French</hi> Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity from the yoak of poverty and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, the two greateſt wants that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to man: but though your liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity this way be very profitable, yet it is in a manner particular, extending but to a certain number of gentlemen. Now by this eſtabliſhment it will become univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, all the youth of the Kingdome may
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152885:57"/>partake of it; and thoſe who live not in the age wherein they may profit by your example, will be inſtructed through your care and bounty. The Nobility for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain honors you, and frequents your court, more through duty, and inclination, then for any particular intereſt. And Sir give me leave to tell you, that by this foundation you will moſt powerfully win all their hearts to your ſervice. The Parents, whoſe greateſt care is for the good bringing up of their children, will bleſs your deſigne, and you ſhall be an occaſion of joy in all families, which were often wont to their great grief to ſee thoſe who ſhould be their glory and chief ſtay, prove ignorant, rude, and groſs, (I will not ſay brutiſh) all their life time. We may both in Court and Country find Dancers, Fencers, and the like enow; But men capable of negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, managing of affairs of moment, knowing the humors of nations and how to take the beſt advantages thereupon of ſuch men, I ſay there is but a very ſmall number to be had any where: which cauſeth your Eminency to be ſo much oppreſſed with buſineſs, being your ſelf forced to have a vigilant eye, and aſſiſting hand every where, both within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the Kingdom and to bear the burthen of the whole ſtate, having none to eaſe or aſſiſt you.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:152885:57"/>
            <p>Strangers have long expected this eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, eſpecially the Northern nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who are ſo deſirous to learn the <hi>French</hi> tongue, that they have ſet up ſchooles for the attaining to it, in their own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes; yet with very ſmall profit, becauſe that thoſe which teach it, are not perfect maſters of it themſelves; and beſides, to to learne a language compleatly, it is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely required to abide for a time in that country where it is naturally ſpoken by men, women, and children. Many therefore come over into <hi>France,</hi> where they receive again but little ſatisfaction; for having private and particular maſters, they ſpend peradventure ſome part of the day in ſtudying of <hi>French,</hi> and the reſt of their time they are amongſt their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men, in whoſe company they ſpeak nothing but their own countrie language: whereas if they did dayly meet in aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of <hi>French</hi> Gentlemen, keeping com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with them, and continually hearing the Profeſſors of Sciences, and Maſters of Exerciſes, they would eaſily attain the true countrie accent and pronunciation, and return home well contented and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. Have not they juſt cauſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt us, if we neglect a thing of ſuch great moment, and which would be ſo profitable to us?</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:152885:58"/>
            <p>As ſoone as the newes of this eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment ſhall be divulged, we ſhall ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly have a mighty concourſe of all the Northerne Nobility: and the great men of thoſe Countries will be glad to have ſuch an occaſion to bring up their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the company of the flower of the <hi>French</hi> Youth, to gaine amongſt them that activeneſſe, and civility which is in a manner naturall to them, learning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Sciences, Languages, and Exerciſes. And on the other ſide the <hi>French</hi> without any travaile, by thus frequenting with ſtrangers, ſhall learne the manners, cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes and diſpoſitions of other Nations. By this meanes ſhall ſtrangers taſte the mildneſſe of our Climate, and ſee the ſtatelineſſe of our Government, our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſhall flouriſh in all the Northerne parts, where it is already in ſo much cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, that it is ordinarily ſpoken in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, the Kings of <hi>Poland, Sweden,</hi> and <hi>Denmarkes</hi> Courts, in the <hi>Swiſſers</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and in <hi>Holland;</hi> ſo that it is a kind of ignominie to a Courtier, to have no Knowledge of the <hi>French</hi> tongue. And ſo will the Eccho of your praiſes ſound eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, and your Citty grow famous thorow out the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>Your Citty of <hi>Richelieu</hi> Sir ſtands in a moſt wholſome aire, fruitfull and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152885:58"/>Country and a moſt delightfull ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation. As for the wholſomneſſe of the aire, there are (beſides experience) ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall pregnant reaſons for it. Firſt the ſoile being dry, and ſandy, the ſubterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall vapours cannot lurke nor lie hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den there to corrupt themſelves, &amp; exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling eaſily, finding free paſſage thorow the pores of the Earth, they can not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into malignant exhalations, as might infect the lower region of the aire. Secondly, the City ſtands open and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the moſt wholſome windes, namely the <hi>North</hi> wind, which hath its free paſſage by the plaine of Champigny; and on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> ſide likewiſe, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no let to hinder it from receiving the benigne influences of the Sunne. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe it is cloſe ſheltered from thoſe windes and aires which ordinarily bring contagious diſeaſes and mortalities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; being defended from the Southern wind by a thick and high wood, and from the aire of the Sea by a great hill which is Weſtward.</p>
            <p>The fruitfullneſſe and goodneſſe of the ſoile appeares by the woods the trees ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver growing up to that height in a bad ground, and likewiſe by the Corn and Vines which grow plentifully upon the Counter ſcarfes of the ditches: Briefly in
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152885:59"/>all <hi>Tueaine,</hi> which is eſteemed to be the Garden of <hi>France,</hi> there are not rarer Gardens, nor producing better fruits. As for the ſuperficies of the Earth, it is cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a great quantity of Simples of ſurpaſſing virtue, and the inſide is reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with various Mines of Sulphur, Bitume, Vitrioll, and Iron, and the very Caſtle and town ditches were full of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Springs, which could not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved becauſe they lay too low. Now theſe Mineralls, and Simples can not chuſe but fill the aire with wholeſome va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours and ſpirits, which continually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hale from them, and purifie and free it from corruption. The Scituation is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther high nor low, in a plaine Country, a moſt temperate Climate, watered by the <hi>Mable,</hi> a ſmall River running by <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelieu,</hi> well woodded with lofty Trees, which are certaine evidences of the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the houſe, tapiſtred with Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, with ſmall hills riſing amidſt them, from which one may of all ſides diſcover the horizon, by which our view is pleaſantly bounded by an equall diſtance from the Towne; there growing Vines upon the ſaid hills that produce moſt excellent Wine. Now ſeeing the aire of its owne Nature is alike in all places, and that the goodneſſe or malignity of it
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152885:59"/>proceeds from the celeſtiall influences, the ſoile, the Scituation, and the windes, which fill it with good or ill vapouts; which wee breathing amidſt, are the chiefe cauſe of our good, or bad conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: Seeing I ſay all theſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces concurre ſo favourably, it would be abſurd to ſay that the aire is not milde and benigne in that City and places ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning, and it was queſtionleſſe thorow the concurrences of ſo many rare quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that this Country brought forth the moſt powerfull Genius, and ſublimed Spirit, that ever was Known in <hi>France.</hi> And though your Eminencie was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to give the water its courſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row certain channels; that was not by reaſon of its deadneſſe or mooriſhneſſe; there being no marſhes or ſtanding pools in that County, but it was to draine the water out of ſome ponds which formerly encompaſſed an old ruinated Caſtle.</p>
            <p>The City was indeed at firſt incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated by certain wells, whoſe waters communicating of the quality and taſte of ſome Mines, were not fitting for common uſe; But your Eminencie conſidering that the goodneſſe of waters was one of the chiefeſt things that belonged to a mans health, and therefore the <hi>Romans</hi> in their encamping would alwaies make
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152885:60"/>choice of ſuch places as had wholeſome waters in them: You Sir have cauſed ſpring waters to be brought from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out by Pipes and Conduits, both into the Towne and Caſtle, which preſerve the Inhabitants in perfect health. Wee muſt confeſſe that at the firſt, when they began to work there, the digging up of the ground did much incommodate the workmen, who lying many times upon the ground, attracted the moiſture there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: and the very buildings, when they were new, cauſed diſeaſes amongſt their firſt inhabitants. But ſuch diſcommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as theſe are likely in all places<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And have wee not in our daies ſeen, when they firſt built upon the Church Mariſhes, they were hardly habitable, and many of thoſe who dwelt there firſt dyed, and now there is not a braver place about <hi>Paris?</hi> it is the habitation of an infinite number of Ladies of quality, who are alwaies excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding carefull of preſerving their healths. And now likewiſe in <hi>Richelieu</hi> people of all ages, and ſexes, live in ſuch perfect health, that though the Town be full of people of all trades, yet no Phyſicians have as yet habited themſelves there ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no employment there for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
            <p>If any falſe reports have paſſed thereof
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152885:60"/>in former times, wee muſt impute it to the malice and omulation of the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourning townes, which envying this cittyes greatneſſe and glory, have bin the Authors and raiſers of them: and falſe rumors have this common with rivers, that the further they run, the more they increaſe: ſo theſe calumnies have been ſpread far into remote countries, and to the Court it ſelf, where it hath been reported, that the country was contagious, and in a manner inhabitable: and ſome officers of this city have alſo cauſed this ſuſpition to increaſe, who having land and buſineſſes elſewhere, to have a pretence to abſent themſelves from home, where by their places they were bound to reſide, have ſeconded thoſe ſlanderous reports: which things have heretofore hindred many from comming to ſettle their abode amongſt us, and have been no ſmall hindrance to our affairs. But Sir, ſince your Academy hath been ſetled in this your citty, the profeſſors thereof have ſo ſtoutly oppoſed this error, upon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall occaſions, that people are now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceived, and thoſe falſe rumors being to ceaſe, truth appearing dayly to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>Finally if the Scituation of the citty of <hi>Riche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieu</hi> be advantagious the ſtructure and ſabrick thereof is alſo moſt admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152885:61"/>Can there be a more ſtately and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent ſight, then ſuch a row of houſes, or rather Palaces, as are all uniformely built in that long and ſpacious ſtreet which leades from the Royal place, (where our Academy ſtands) to the Cardinall place, where you have built that Stately Church, which is a magnificent and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall monument of your piety? Can there be any ſtatelier or compleater buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, then the Caſtle, with its Courts, Park, Channels, Gardens, and other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendencies belonging to it? Were ever ſo many rare and excellent peeces of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, all manner of Arts ſeen toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, eſpecially for Tapiſtry, Sculpture, and Painting? Your Gallery, wherein are drawn to the life the battells won, victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries obtained, and cityes conquered by his Majeſty? So that <hi>Greece Italy,</hi> and all other places of the world, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned for their induſtry and curioſity, ſeem to have been ſpolyed of their moſt precious ornaments to adorn the place of your birth. But I will not undertake par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to deſcribe all the rarities of this place; they would fill up a volume. I will therfore be content o ſay onely thus much, that they come hither already from all parts, as they did in former times to the Oracles, to behold thoſe rare Antiquities
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152885:61"/>which were admired throughout the world.</p>
            <p>Wee may therefore truly ſay, that <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelieu</hi> is a moſt fitting and convenient place to ſettle your Academy in. Firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the inhabitants themſelves ſpeak as pure <hi>French,</hi> as can be ſpoken in any part of <hi>France;</hi> which is a great advantage, ſeeing the deſign could hardly take eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in a place where ill Language were ſpoken. Secondly, the Countrie round about it abounds with all manner of commoditie, it is ſituated at equall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, from the Rivers of <hi>Loire,</hi> and <hi>Vienna,</hi> which are the beſt nurſes <hi>France</hi> hath: and likewiſe from the havens of <hi>Brittanny,</hi> and <hi>Poitou,</hi> from whence may be had all manner of things conducing to mans life: it ſtands in a place of repoſe, retired from turmoil, and negotiations of traffick, ſelected as it were a purpoſe for men ſeriouſly and quietly to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wholly to Diſcipline and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly it ſtands almoſt in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and center of all <hi>France,</hi> amidſt thoſe Provinces where the worſt <hi>French</hi> is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; Low <hi>Brittanny,</hi> the lower <hi>Poitou, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigord, Limoſin, Auvergne, Gaſcoigne,</hi> and other Countries there about, from whence they may the more conveniently ſend their
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152885:62"/>youths to amend and correct their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and learne the true accent and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is near the River <hi>Loyre,</hi> upon the bankes whereof all ſtrangers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to be, for the moſt part in <hi>Orleans, Bloys, Tours, Saumur, Angiers, Nantes,</hi> and all thoſe Cities by which that faire River runnes. And finally beſides all theſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of Scituation, your Eminence when you pleaſe may endow it with ſuch franchiſes and immunities as you ſhall think fit, &amp; as other Princes and eminent men have done, who have founded Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and Univerſities.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this word Academie is now of late moſt improperly appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Gymnaſtick,</hi> and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing of youth in the Art of riding, by ſuch as know not the property of termes: whereby that Luſtre of this foundation might be eclipſed, and ſtrangers cauſed to imagine the Academies of <hi>Richelieu</hi> to be like other Academies, appointed one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the compleating the carriage of the body, and adorning the outward behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: Wee have thought it fitting in this place to make known, that the art of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is but one particular thing taught in our Academie which being ſet up by the name of a Royall Colledge, is, to ſpeake
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:152885:62"/>properly, a true Vniverſity of Sciences, whereunto your Eminencie hath thought good to adde as acceſſory, and depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereon, the Art of managing of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and other Exerciſes of the body; to leave unto poſterity, in the place where you were born, a compleat and perfect Modell for education of Gentry and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and to reform the diſorders which were crept into other Colledges and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademies of this Kingdome, where theſe two ſorts of perfections are taught ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, againſt the Maximes of all the Politicians as have been in former ages: who were all of opinion, that the Mind, and Body, of man the two eſſentiall parts of our being, ought to be exerciſed, and inſtructed both at one time. Becauſe that even as the Exerciſe of the Body, without that of the Mind, breeds a kind of Cruelty, and Inſolencie in us; even ſo the Exerciſe of the Minde, without that of the Body, cauſeth a kind of Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſtupidity. Wherefore your Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie, who knowes better then any, how much it concernes the ſtate, to have its Nobles throwly poſſeſſed, and qualified with rare qualities both of body and mind; hath moſt prudently ordered, that of thoſe eight Profeſſors, whereof this Academy chiefly cenſiſts, ſix ſhould be
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152885:63"/>for Sciences, and the other two for Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes. To this we may adde, that Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities both in antient and Moderne times have alwaies been, and ſtill are called by the name of Academies; witneſſe thoſe of <hi>Alexandria, Athens, Paris, Alcala,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other.</p>
            <p>Thus your Eminencie in reuniting the Exerciſes of the body to thoſe of the mind, procures this advantage to your Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, that it being a Nurſerie for Sciences, which ordinarily attract a concourſe of youth from all parts, there will never be any want of Schollers for the Exerciſes of the body, as Fencing, Dancing, Riding, and the like, whereby the teachers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being in continuall employment, this Academie will not be ſubject to thoſe failings, as others, which are not kept up by Sciences, and one day have ſtore of Schollars, and the next day are without any.</p>
            <p>And finally I know that this City, by reaſon of its name, and eminent qualities of the founder, is already famous through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all this Kingdome, and amongſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain Nations alſo. So that if your Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie continue your favour towards this deſign, your Academie wil cauſe this to be one of the moſt populous and flouriſhing Cities of <hi>Europe;</hi> not leſſe renouned then
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152885:63"/>other Cities, which our Kings have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored with the Profeſſions of Divinitie, Canon and Civill Law, Phyſick and Arts; and equall to either <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> or <hi>Alexandria,</hi> or any other ancient Cities of <hi>Greece,</hi> with all theiry ceums and Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coes.</p>
            <p>There are ſeverall waies to make Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties populous, and adorned, namely Commerce, Jurisdictions, Franchiſes and immunities, Trades, and Handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts. But the moſt noble way of ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and renouning of them, is by means of Sciences, which were the cauſe that <hi>Memphis</hi> in <hi>Egypt, Athens</hi> in <hi>Greece, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> in <hi>Italie,</hi> and <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> have grown up to ſuch magnificence, that they have drawn all Nations of the world to come and behold them with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="statutes">
            <pb facs="tcp:152885:64"/>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:152885:64"/>
            <head>STATUTES AND ORDINANCES For the Government Of the Academie, or Royall Colledge, founded by Order from the King, in the Gity of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelieu:</hi> Under the protection of the Dukes of <hi>Richelieu.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Royal Academie, eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the City of <hi>Richelieu,</hi> ſhall be governed by a Director, or Superviſor.</p>
            <p>The Superviſor ſhall take the Oath of Allegeance to the King, before the Duke of <hi>Richelieu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Superviſor ſhal appoint men to ſupply the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es as ſhall fall void, either by death or otherwiſe,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152885:65"/>who after they have been there a year or two, ſhall be preſented to the King by the Superviſor, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their letters Patents, if the Profeſſors find them worthie thereof. And during their ſaid time of Regency or Probation, they ſhall enjoy the ſame Rights and Emoluments, as other Profeſsors doe.</p>
            <p>The Superviſor ſhall not depoſe or diſplace any Profeſſor, without the generall conſent of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>The Superviſor ſhall provide ſchoolmaſters and Officers for the ſaid Academy, who ſhall have reaſonable and ſufficient wages aſſigned them.</p>
            <p>The Superviſor ſhall have power to ſettle School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters and School miſtreſses: to whom he ſhall preſcribe a Method, to teach the children of the city to read and write well.</p>
            <p>The ſuperviſor ſhall have power to call and break off all aſſemblies, as ſhall be to deliberate upon affairs touching the commonalty, wherein all things ſhall be decided by Plurality of voices.</p>
            <p>The Dean, or Ancienteſt Profeſſor, ſhall ſupply the ſuperviſors place in his abſence, and performe his office.</p>
            <p>The Academy ſhall be provided with moveables and utenſiles, at the common charge of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors; and if any of them chance to dy, or leave his place, the part and portion which he ſhall have in the common goods, ſhall be kept for him or his heires, according to the eſtimation as ſhall be made thereof by the ſaid Profeſſors.</p>
            <p>The Incomes which ſhall be received of the Scholars, ſhall be laid in Common, and divided
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152885:65"/>equally between the Superviſor, Profeſſors, Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rider, and Maſter of Defence:</p>
            <p>The Superviſor having firſt deducted the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth part thereof for other Maſters wages, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Servants, and other charges needfull for the maintenance of the Academy.</p>
            <p>The Profeſſors, as near as poſſible may be, ſhall of themſelves ſupply all the claſſes one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſhall ſucceſſively teach all the Sciences.</p>
            <p>The Profeſsors, to perfect themſelves every day more and more in the Sciences, ſhall dayly conferre one hour in the day concerning their ſtudies; and what the one knoweth not, the other ſhall be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to teach him.</p>
            <p>The Profeſſors of Sciences ſhall take their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in all aſſemblies after the Superviſor, according to the order and time of their reception, and after them the Querry, or Horſe rider, and Fence ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            <p>The Profeſsors ſhall in their turnes every ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day cauſe publick diſputations to be held.</p>
            <p>The Profeſſors, according to the antient cuſtome of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſhall not dictate any writings in the claſſis for Sciences: every one ſhall have his book printed, and by that meanes, the time which ſhould be ſpent in writing, ſhall be more profitably employed in repetitions, and diſputations.</p>
            <p>The Profeſsors ſhall not uſe any books in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Sciences and Languages, unleſſe they have been firſt examined and approved of by the whole company.</p>
            <p>The Profeſſors ſhall carefully teach their ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and cauſe them often to rehearſe the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152885:66"/>Diviſions, Theoremes, and Propoſitions of Sciences and Arts.</p>
            <p>The Profeſſors ſhall finiſh their courſe of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy in ſix years, teaching the Sciences, Arts, and Humanity in ſix diſlinct Claſses, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Namely</hi> In the ſixt Glaſſis they ſhall teach <hi>Grammar,</hi> the <hi>Card</hi> in <hi>Plane, Chronologie,</hi> and <hi>Geneologie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fifth, <hi>Hiſtory, Mythology, Poeſie,</hi> and Rhetorick.</p>
            <p>In the fourth, Logick and Morall Philoſophy, <hi>Namely</hi> Monaſticall, Oeconomicall, and Politicall.</p>
            <p>In the third, the Elements of Geometry, and Arithmetick, together with the practice of both of them, and Muſick.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond, Naturall Philoſophy in generall, and particular, with Phyſiologie, and Pathologie, and Metaphyſicks.</p>
            <p>In the firſt, the Mechanicks, the Opticks, &amp;c. Aſtrologie, Geography, and the Gnomonicks.</p>
            <p>The ſame Profeſsors, who in the morning taught Sciences, ſhall in the afternoon teach Languages, in order as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Namely,</hi> In the ſixt Claſſis they ſhall teach the Rudiments, <hi>Colloquies, Cato</hi> &amp; <hi>Onomaſia,</hi> or <hi>Nomenclature,</hi> conformable to things as well natural as artificial.</p>
            <p>In the fifth, Grammar, writing of Epiſtles, the Curious Method, and <hi>Commenius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fourth, the Quantities, <hi>Terence, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race, Quintus Curtius,</hi> and the Poets.</p>
            <p>In the third, the Figures, <hi>Tullies Offices, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152885:66"/>Caeſars</hi> Commentaries, and Orators.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond, the Principles of the <hi>Greeke</hi> tongue, and the preheminence which it hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove other languages.</p>
            <p>In the firſt, the Origine and Genius of the <hi>Greek, Latin, Italian, Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> tongues, the conformity and difference that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
            <p>The Querry, or Horſe-maſter, Fence-maſtor, and other inferior Maſters ſhall teach their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Exerciſes every day at a certain houre, but the Schollers divided into ſeveral companies, ſhall come to learn but once in two daies, according to ſuch order as ſhall be appointed them.</p>
            <p>On Feſtivalls and Holidaies, the Querry or horſerider ſhall appoint running at the ring, and at the Quintune; and the Fence maſter ſhall cauſe his Scholars to Exerciſe on thoſe daies publickly, and ſometimes fight at Barriers.</p>
            <p>The Scholars ſhall be bred up in the feare of God, and their due allegeance and obedience to their King. The Scholars ſhall joyntly learn Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, Languages, and Exerciſes, at ſuch houres as ſhall be ſet down by the Superviſor, who ſhall alſo have power to diſpenſe with any of them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lawful occaſion.</p>
            <p>Every week there ſhall be one play day appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for all the Scholars.</p>
            <p>The Claſſes ſhall alwaies open the next day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Saint <hi>Luke's</hi> day, and the Vacations ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the firſt day of <hi>September.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt fifteen daies of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> they ſhall publickly diſpute upon general poſitions in all Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:152885:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>according to the Orders of the ſix Claſses. And every Profeſſor ſhall in his turne be a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator in thoſe diſputations, concerning ſuch things as he hath taught all the yeare; and all the other Masters ſhall cauſe their Scholars publickly to do Exerciſes in their ſeveral profeſſions.</p>
            <p>And to encourage the Scholars to the ſtudying of Sciences, and learning of Exerciſes, they ſhall have certain prizes, or rewards distributed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, according to their merits, by the Profeſsors.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152885:67"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152885:68"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
